<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ophthalmos aplois or the single eye, entituled the vision of God wherein is infolded the mistery of divine presence, so to be in one place finitely in apperance, as yet in every place no lesse present, and whilst Hee is here, Hee is universally every where infinitely himselfe. Penned by that learned Dr. Cusanus, and published for the good of the saints. By Giles Randall.</title>
            <title>De visione Dei. English.</title>
            <author>Nicholas, of Cusa, Cardinal, 1401-1464.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 102 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87711</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K395</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1212_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208815</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867737</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120060</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87711)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120060)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 168:E1212[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ophthalmos aplois or the single eye, entituled the vision of God wherein is infolded the mistery of divine presence, so to be in one place finitely in apperance, as yet in every place no lesse present, and whilst Hee is here, Hee is universally every where infinitely himselfe. Penned by that learned Dr. Cusanus, and published for the good of the saints. By Giles Randall.</title>
                  <title>De visione Dei. English.</title>
                  <author>Nicholas, of Cusa, Cardinal, 1401-1464.</author>
                  <author>Randall, Giles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 178, [2] p.,plate.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Streater, at the signe of the Bible in Budge-Row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dr. Cusanus = Nicholas of Cusa.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: De visione Dei.</note>
                  <note>The first two words of the title are in Greek letters.</note>
                  <note>With blank leaf A1 and a final blank leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Attributes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:120060:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:120060:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>traveler beholds globe</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> OR THE VISION OF GOD <hi>by that learned D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cusanus</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thou calſt all things out of nothing, and they are.</p>
                  <p>Are to be ſould by Io: Streater at the ſigne of the Bible in budg roe 1646. cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:120060:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Οφσαλμις Απλυς OR The ſingle Eye, Entituled the Viſion OF GOD</p>
            <p>Wherein is infolded the Miſtery of Divine preſence, So to be in one place finitely in apperance, as yet in every place no leſſe preſent, and whilſt Hee is here, Hee is univerſally every where infinitely himſelfe. Penned by that Learned Dr. CVSANVS, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed for the good of the Saints.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GILES RANDALL.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 139. 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>VVhither ſhall I flie from thy Spirit,</l>
               <l>VVhither ſhall I go from thy preſence.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>John Streater,</hi> at the Signe of the Bible in <hi>Budge-Row.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:120060:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:120060:3"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE To the Reader.</head>
            <p>NOthing is, or ever was endeavoured, by most men, with more induſtry, and leſſe ſucceſſe, than the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the true God. And as in the viſion and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him ſtandeth<note n="(a)" place="margin">Joh. 17 3.</note> life Eternall; So in the non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, or wrong know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:120060:4"/>of him, or any thing for him which is not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, lyeth all loſſe and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. This point therefore being that one thing neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the true knowledge or darke ignorance, whereof confiſteth life and death, good and evill, God and the Devill, if this corner ſtone be rightly founded, and the whole structure ſuperſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereon, it proveth wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms houſe, withſtandeth all aſſaults, &amp; tryals, but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is the houſe of folly, and the Tower of confuſion and deſtruction. That there is a God, almoſt all men are convinced.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:120060:4"/>
            <p>But who or what this God is, almoſt all men are ignorant of. After the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and worſhip of this God, all men are ſo principled and carried on; that rather then they will be, or thought to be without him, and the knowledge of him, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will creat his Creator, to himſelfe, and his fancy ſhall give eſſence and being to this God.</p>
            <p>All men may be reduced under foureheads or notions; first there are Atheiſts who owne no God. Secondly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt knowne ignorant, who acknowledge implicitly a God but him to them an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne
<pb facs="tcp:120060:5"/>God. Thirdly there are the ignorant knowers, who thinking they know God, know nothing elſe than God ſetting up ſome thing for God which by nature is not God. Fourthly there are the true knowers who know the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Joh. 17 3.</note> only true God truly. The firſt hath not ſo much as a conceit of a God, The ſecond conceives a God but ignorantly without ſubſtance or ſo much as Image who or what. The third doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a God not in ſubſtance but Image, The fourth not conceives, but knowes, not God in Image, but eſſence, and ſubſtance, not any thing
<pb facs="tcp:120060:5"/>for God but the true and ſubſtantiall God of theſe foure ſtates of men, the laſt only is the ſtate of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, The other three ſtates of ignorance, which ariſe from their proper cauſe, darkneſſe: And that is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive in the firſt, Negative in the ſecond, Privative in the third ſtate, But light it ſelfe is only extant and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtent in the laſt ſtate. The first errs in denying a God, The ſecond in not knowing a God, the third in not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true God, and this two wayes either in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective or Adverbe, in the Adjective, they know not
<pb facs="tcp:120060:6"/>the true God, or in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe they know not this true God truly Many are guilty of the first errour, more of the ſecond, most of the third, but few and few<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st are the partakers of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the last. And as there is gradation in the three firſt ſtates, ſo is there in the evill of them, the first bad, the ſecond worſe, the third worst, and ſo much is it the worſt as it is Satani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sformed into an Angell of light, it being Religious, Sublimate, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <p>Reader by what hath bin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpoken thou maist gather
<pb facs="tcp:120060:6"/>that God is either knowne or not knowne, if not known whence it fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w s either from poſitive, Negative, or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative darkneſſe, and of all theſe the laſt is worst where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in man is moſt active and ſeemingly ſeeing and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. How miſerable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are we deceived who the more we ſeeke, the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are off from the true knowledge and finding out of God: that herefore thou maiſt herein be premoniſhed and premunite againſt ſuch mistakes, obſerve that God is one ſimple infinite indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible being, and muſt be knowne as he is which no
<pb facs="tcp:120060:7"/>finite can do or be capable of. Some men becauſe they acknowledge from many undeniable principles that he is infinite, are ſo elevated that they abſtract him as they think from all things, and think they have found his true being when as the truth is, they that abſtract him from all things as being to infinite for all things; do herein yet miſtake, for he is in the creation, and there to be knowne, for although God is neither any one thing, many things or all things of your creation, yet is hee all and in all, and by us to bee ſeene cleerely therein, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:120060:7"/>all and in all, <hi>p. 19. Rom.</hi> 1. Yea when they have aprehended him above all yet do they confirme him within their owne fancies and imaginations which are no leſſe finite than any other thing. Thus they deale with him as the people in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> with their wooden Gods, they hew, chop, ſhred, and out off what ſeemeth them good, &amp; when it is brought to the Idea of their own brain then it is God, and the reſt they burn as not eſſentiall to that God they have ſhaped out to themſelves, and this is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ne the god head and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine eſſence with the whole
<pb facs="tcp:120060:8"/>glory of the Goſpell into meere conceit and ſublimat vanity, and this is ſpirituall and inviſible Idolatry, even as to make corporeall ſhapes and ſenſible appearances of him is groſſe viſible, and bodily Idolatry.</p>
            <p>Be thou admoniſhed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian brother in this point; it is the eaſieſt matter that may be to miſcarry herein, it being the nigheſt and dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt of all ſecrets, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God conſiſteth in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites and contradictories to the wiſdome of the fleſh, and he is leaſt knowne by reaſon of his ſeeming like that which not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:120060:8"/>is fartheſt from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for as all being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall and reall hath alſo a falſe, and imaginary being the ſhaddow of the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; as the height hath its oppoſite, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c So there is the true God and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary even the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, and as in materiall ſubstances, not the eſſence or ſubstance is the object of ſence but cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour magnitude, and other accidents, even ſo not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eſſence of God is the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſence, but ſomething for God in the ſeat of God, being nothing eſſe than God, and contrary to God. But the ſound and unerring know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:120060:9"/>of him ſtandeth in your knowledge of your man Chriſt Ieſus, and whoſoever hath ſeene him hath ſeene the Father alſo, for he is not a dead<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of him, but lively or living<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Image of the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God, yea the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Tim. 3.16. Mat. 1.23.</note> fulgor or brightneſſe of his glory, and character of his perſon, for God is manifeſt in the fleſh which is the great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of godlineſſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6.</note> and till hee be <hi>Emmanuell</hi> God with us, God in us, there is no true viſion or knowledge of him, for as nothing is in the underſtanding, but what is in the ſence, firſt and as
<pb facs="tcp:120060:9"/>nothing in the ſence is a vaileable till it live in the light of the underſtanding within and at home; ſo there is no true living knowledge of God within us, till he be in us formed in the face of Ieſus Chriſt. This is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine argument of this little worke ſelected, and cull'd out of the moſt elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate peeces of that learned Dr. <hi>Cuſanus;</hi> whoſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment herein is chiefly and only to ſhaddow forth unto thee, the being and exiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the infinite God with and in the finite; which is ſutable to the ſtate of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipient ſubject, for becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:120060:10"/>the infinite cannot bee infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly received by the finite, nor can the infinite become finite as in himſelfe, yet is he ſo in the finits capability as finite and contracted, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himſelfe forth in a wonderfull manner ſo, that he that is immoveable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, and the unchangeable changeth with thee, and though no alterationin time, place or other thing can bee unto him or in him. Yet is he ſo immoveable as yet mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veable and ſo inſeperably aſsiſtent with his creature in every thing that hee that is neither here nor there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly is yet here and there,
<pb facs="tcp:120060:10"/>and ſo heere as if not there, and ſo with thee as if with none elſe, wonderouſly giving himſelfe all to every one, as if he were all but to one, ſo that if the expreſsions may be borne withall, hee is finitly infinite, and infinitly finite, he is immoveably mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evable, &amp; meveably immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veable, the Active and the Paſsive, the receiver and the received, becauſe he that is infinitly above thee, makes himſelfe to bee to thee what he is in thee and makes thee to be what thou art in him, he cloathes himſelfe with fleſh, reaſon, ſence, and the forme and nature of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb facs="tcp:120060:11"/>who yet is above all and Lord over all, this is a high and hard ſaying, who can beare it, yet I ſay unto thee Reader, if God give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, a ſeing eye, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding heart to read, and this author in the ſpirit of light and truth, theſe things will bee eaſier and more facile to thee which is the deſire which he deſireth for thee who is a lover of thee in the truth of Ieſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:120060:11"/>
            <head>AN <hi>INTRODVCTION</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Will now lay open unto you my dearly beloved Brethren, what I had before promiſed concerning the eaſineſſe of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Divinity, for I Judge you whom I know to be led with a zeale of God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to have this treaſure opened unto you, though very precious and moſt fruitfull: But firſt I beſeech the Almighty who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can expreſſe and declare himſelfe to give me his word from above, and utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that according to your capacity, I may expound theſe wonders which are revealed above and beyond the ſight of ſence, reaſon and underſtanding: And I will endeavour after the moſt ſimple and ordinary manner to bring you experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally into the moſt ſacred darkneſſe where while you ſhall be feeling and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the preſence of the unapproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able light, every one of you ſhall attempt in the beſt man that God ſhall give you leave continually to come neerer and neerer and here by a moſt ſweet morſell to foretaſt that ſupper of eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereunto we are called in the word of life by the Goſpell of Chriſt bleſſed for evermore.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:120060:12"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>OF all the meanes whereby I can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after the manner of men to liſt you up to divine things, J held it beſt to doe it by a ſimititude: But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt humane workes, I found no I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage more fit and convenient for our purpoſe, then the Image of one that ſees all things, where though there bee every where great ſtore, yet leaſt you ſhould faile in the practiſe, which requires ſuch a ſencible figure, <hi>I</hi> ſend your Charity ſuch a Table as I could have for the preſent, containing a Picture of one that lookes every way which <hi>I</hi> call the Image of God (man:) This you ſhall faſten in ſome place, for example on a Northwall, and then ſhall all you Brethren ſtand about it, a little diſtance from it, and looke upon it, and every one of you ſhall finde by exporience, that from what place ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be lookes-upon the ſame, it ſhall ſeem that none but himſelfe alone is ſeene or looked upon by the Picture, and that Brother that ſtands on the eaſt ſide of it, will imagine that the face lookes eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly at him only, ſo bee that ſtands on the ſouth ſide will think it lookes ſoutherly, and he on the weſt weſterly; And firſt you will wonder how it can be that it ſhould look upon you all, and every one of you at once, for the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:120060:12"/>of him that ſtands in the Eaſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive the Ficture looking any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way namely to the weſt, or the ſouth, Then let the Brother which was in the Eaſt place himſelfe in the weſt, and hee ſhall perceive the countenance fixed on him in the weſt as it was before, when it was in the Eaſt, and becauſe he knows the Picture to be fixed and unmoved, he will admire the change of the unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able countenance, And if fixing his eye on the Image, he walketh from the weſt to the Eaſt, be will finde that the eye of the Picture goes continually along with him, and if from the Eaſt he returne to the weſt, it will in like manner not forſake him, and be will wonder how it was unmoveably moved, Neither ſhall his imagination be able to conceive how it ſhould poſſibly be moved with another that meets him, and goes with a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry motion, And if for further tryall, hee makes his Brother looking ſtill upon the Image, go from the Eaſt to the VVeſt, whilſt himſelfe at the ſame time goes from the VVeſt to the Eaſt, and meeting him, ask him if the eye or ſight of the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture go along with him, and ſhall heare that it doth ſo (though it go along with himſelfe too) he will beleeve him, and if be ſhould not beleeve him, he would not
<pb facs="tcp:120060:13"/>think it poſsibe, and ſo by his Brothers relation, and telling him hew ill come at length to know that the countenance of the Picture accompanies all men though they go contrary wayes.</p>
            <p>Hee ſhall therefore finde by experience that that immoveable face is ſo moved to the Eaſt, that it is at the ſame time likewiſe moved to the VVeſt, and ſo to the South, that is it likewiſe moved to the North, and ſo to one place that it is alſo moved to all places, and ſo relates to one motion, that it relates to all at one and whilst bee cunſiders how that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage forſakes no man, hee ſees likewiſe how it takes ſo dilligent care of everiy one, and ſeemes to obſerve him who looks upon it, ſo particularly as if it took care for no body elſe, in ſo much that it cannot be conceived by him whom it beholds how it ſhould looke after any body elſe, And be ſhall further perceive how it takes as particular notice of the leaſt Creature, as it doth of the greateſt, and of the whole univerſe.</p>
            <p>Now from this ſenſible appearance my purpoſe is to lift up you, my moſt beloved Brethren, by a certaine practiſe of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto miſticall divinity, when I ſhall have premiſed three things neceſſary hereto.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120060:13"/>
            <head>The Viſion of God.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>That the perfection of appearance is verified of the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect GOD.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
               <p>HEre in the firſt place wee muſt ſuppoſe that nothing can appeare about the ſight of the Image of God, but that it is much more truely in the ſight
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120060:14"/>or viſion of God for God which is the height of all perfection, and greater then can bee thought is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Greek becauſe he ſees and beholds all things.</p>
               <p>Therefore if a painted face can appeare in an Image, as if it look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon all things, and every thing at once, certainely this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the perfection of ſight can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not leſſe truely agree unto the truth, than it doth apparently to the Image or appearance: For if one ſight bee in us more ſharpe and quick than another, and ſcarſe diſcerning the things that are neer, and another diſcerning the things that are far off, and reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the object quickly, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſlowly, there can be no doubt but that the abſolute ſight (from which is, all the ſight of things that ſee excells all the ſharpnes, ſwiftneſſe, and ſtrength of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l that actually doe ſee, or that can bee made to ſee.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:120060:14"/>
               <p>For if I looke to ſight in the abſtract which I have in my mind free from all eyes and Organs, and conſider how that abſtracted ſight in his contracted being, namely as they that ſee, doe ſee by that ſight is contracted unto time to the ſeverall parts of clymates of the world, to ſingular and indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall objects; &amp; to all other ſuch like conditions, and that ſight in the abſtract is on the other ſide as much drawne away, freed, acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and abſolved from thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. Then I very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that it is not of the eſſence of ſight to reſpect or looke upon one object more then another, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it inſeparable accompany ſight, in the contracted being thereof, that whilſt it looks upon one thing it cannot looke upon another, or abſolutely upon all things. But God as he is the true uncontracted ſight or ſeeing is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120060:15"/>not leſſe than may by the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be conceived of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract ſight, but beyond all propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, more perfect, wherefore the appearance of ſight in the Picture cannot ſo well as the conceipt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach or come neere the height of the excellency of abſolute vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or ſight, and conſequently it is no whit to be doubted, but that whatſoever appeares in that Image is excellently and perfectly in the abſolute ſight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>That abſolute ſight comprehends all manner of ſeeing.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 2.</head>
               <p>NOw thou muſt after theſe things underſtand that ſight is varied in things that ſee, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the varietie of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction thereof for our ſight fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the affections of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans and the minde, therefore
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120060:15"/>ſome one man looke now loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and chearfully, by and by ſadly and angerly, one while childiſhly, then manly, afterwards ſeriouſly, and agedly. But ſight freed from all, contraction doth at once and altogether comprehend all and every manner of ſeeing, as being the moſt adequate meaſure and true examplar of all ſight: for without abſolute ſight, there can be no contracted ſight, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſight comprehends in it ſelfe all manners of ſeeing, and ſo alſo that every one and yet remaines utterly free and abſolute from all varietie, for in abſolute ſight are all the manners of contradictions of ſeeing uncontractedly; For every contradiction is in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, for abſolute ſight is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction; of contradictions it being an incontractible contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; Therfore a moſt ſimple con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raction <hi>Covieides,</hi> or is the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:120060:16"/>ſame with an abſolute, And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contraction no thing is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, ſo abſolute viſion or ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is in every ſight, becauſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry contracted ſeeing is by it, and cannot be at all without it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>That the things which are ſpoken or affirmed of God doe not differ really.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 3.</head>
               <p>ENter next into a ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration how all things that are ſaid or affirmed of God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not really differ, becauſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the higheſt and moſt perfect ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of him thought we in diverſe reſpects aſcribe divers names and Attributes unto him; But God being the abſolute reaſons; or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all formall reaſons compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cateth, or foldeth up in himſelfe all reaſons; whereupon we attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:120060:16"/>unto God ſeeing, hearing, taſting, ſmelling touching, ſence, reaſon, and underſtanding and ſuch like, according to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſons of the ſignification of every word, yet in him ſeeing is not another diſtinct thing from hearing, taſting, touching ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and underſtanding, and ſo all Divinity is ſaid to be put in a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, becauſe one of his Attributes is affirmed of another. And for God to have a thing is for him to be that thing, or his having is his being his moving is his ſtanding, his running is his reſting, and in like manner all his other Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, ſo that although we aſcribe unto him, moving in one reſpect, and ſtanding in another, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is the abſolute reaſon in which all alterity or otherneſſe is unitie or oneneſſe, and all diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie is Ioencitie or ſelfe ſame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Therefore that diverſitie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:120060:17"/>of reaſons or formality (as wee conceive diverſity, which is not Identity it ſelfe) cannot bee in God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>That Gods Viſion or ſight is called his providence, his Grace Eternall life.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 4.</head>
               <p>VNto the Image of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach thou now my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that giveſt thy ſelfe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation. And firſt place thy ſelfe in the Eaſt, then in the South and laſtly in the Weſt. And becauſe the ſight or eye of the Picture looks upon thee every where a like, &amp; forſakes thee not whetherſoever thou goeſt, thou ſhalt be thereby ſtirred up unto ſpeculation and provoked to ſay.</p>
               <p>Lord, in this Image of thee doe I now behold thy providence by a certaine ſencible experience,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120060:17"/>for if thou forſakeſt not mee who am the moſt baſe and vile of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l things, certainely thou wilt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be wanting to any thing. For ſo art thou preſent to all things, and every thing as unto all things and every thing is preſent to that being without which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, and ſo art thou the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute being of all things, preſent to each thing, as if thou tookeſt no care for any thing elſe. And this comes to paſſe becauſe there is nothing but prefers its owne being before any thing elſe, and the manner of its being to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manners of being and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends its owne being, that it had rather the being of all other things ſhould goe to ruine and diſtruction than its owne. For ſo doſt thou O Lord looke upon every thing that is, that it cannot be conceived by all, that is, that thou haſt any care other then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120060:18"/>that that only thing might be in the beſt manner that it can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be, and that all other things that are may ſerve only to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that that which thou lookeſt upon may be after the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>Thou O Lord doſt not ſuffer me by any imagination to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that thou loveſt any thing elſe beſides mee more than my ſelfe ſeeing thine eye is never of from me alone, And becauſe there the eye is where the love is, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do I finde thou loveſt mee, becauſe thine eyes are alwayes moſt attentively upon me thy ſervant.</p>
               <p>Lord thy ſeeing is loving, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently as thy ſight regardes and lookes upon mee, ſo atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively that it never turnes it ſelfe from me ſo thy ove; And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thy love is alwayes with mee, and thy love is no other
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120060:18"/>thing then thy ſelfe that loveſt mee, therefore thou art alwayes with mee. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d thou forſakeſt me not, thou preferreſt me on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſide, as taking moſt dilligent care of me; Thy being O Lord forſakes not my being, who am only ſo far forth as thou art with me: And thy ſeeing being thy being, therefore I am becauſe thou lookeſt upon me, And if thou hide thy countenance from me, I ſhall not ſubſiſt. But I know that thy ſeeing is that greateſt goodneſſe which cannot but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it ſelfe to every thing capable. Therefore canſt thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forſake me as long as J am capable of thee. To me then it belongs as much as J can to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more and more capable of thee continually: And I know the capacity which makes a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is nothing but likeneſſe, and all incapacity proceeds from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likeneſſe</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:120060:19"/>
               <p>If I therefore make my ſelfe by all poſſible meanes like to thy Goodneſſe, according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of likeneſſe I ſhall be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the truth, thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me O Lord a being, and that ſuch a one as may continually make it ſelfe more capable of thy goodneſſe, and this power which I have from thee wherein I hould the lively Image of the power of thy omnipotency, is that free will by which I may either en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large or reſtraine the capacity of thy grace, enlarge it I ſay by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formaty when I ſtrive to be good becauſe thou art good, juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art juſt, and mercifull, becauſe thou art mercifull when all my endeavour is turned to nothing but thee, becauſe all thy endeavour is turned to me, when I looke moſt attentively to thee alone, and never turne away the eyes of my minde, becauſe thou
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:120060:19"/>embraceſt me with contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all ſight, when I turne my love to thee alone, who being love, art turned to me a lone.</p>
               <p>And Lord what is my life, but thoſe embraces whereby the ſweetneſſe of the love doth ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morouſly compaſſe me, I love my life exceedingly, becauſe thou art the ſweetneſſe of my life.</p>
               <p>I now behold as in a Glaſſe in an Image, in a ſhadow eternall life becauſe it is nothing els but that bleſſed viſion whereby thou never ceaſeſt to ſee and looke upon me moſt lovingly, even to the in moſt of my ſoule. And thy ſeeing is or in thee to ſee is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but to quicken mee continually to ſend unto me the moſt ſweet love of thee, by the ſending of that love to inflame me to the love of thee, by infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to feed me, by feeding mee to ſet my deſires on fire, by fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:120060:20"/>my deſires to give them drink of the dew of gladneſſe, and by giving them drinke to ſend unto me a fountaine of Water, and by ſending that to increaſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate it, and to communicate this immortallity, to give mee the never fading glory of this heavenly, high and greateſt King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to make me partaker of that inheritance which is only thy ſonnes, and to appoint me a, poſſeſſion of that eternall felicity where there is the Garden of all delights that can be deſired than which there can nothing better either be deviſed by Man or Angell or be by any manner of being, for it is the abſolute great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of every rationall deſire, than which a greater cannot be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:120060:20"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>That the viſion of God is called his mercy, his motion and operation.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
               <p>EVer infinite is the multitude of thy ſweetneſſe which thou haſt laid up for them that love thee, for it is an inexplicable trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of gladneſſe moſt full of joy, To taſt that thy ſweetneſſe is by an experimentall touch to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and to lay hold upon the ſweetneſſe of all di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ectable things in their principall or beginning. It is to reach or attaine unto the reaſon and formallity of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable things in thy wiſdome, to ſee therefore the abſolute reaſon or formality which is the reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>formality of all things, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but to taſt thee O God, in the minde becauſe thou art
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120060:21"/>ſweetneſſe it ſelfe, the being of life and underſtanding.</p>
               <p>Thy ſeeing O Lord what is it other when thou lookeſt upon me with the eye of pitty, then that thou art ſeene by me? In ſeeing mee thou giveſt thy ſelfe to be ſeene by me which art <hi>a hidden, an inviſible God.</hi> No man can ſee thee but as farre forth as thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt thy ſelfe to be ſeene; neither is thy being ſeene any thing elſe but that thou ſeeſt him that ſeeth thee.</p>
               <p>I ſee in this thy Image, how prone and ready thou art O Lord to ſhew thy face to all that ſeeke thee, for thou never ſhutteſt thine eyes, nor never turneſt them any other way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I turne my ſelfe away from thee when I turne my ſelfe wholly to any other thing; yet for all this thou changeſt not thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or thy c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>untenance.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:120060:21"/>
               <p>If thou do looke upon me with the eye of grace. I am the cauſe thereof, becauſe I am divided from thee by turning my ſelfe to ſome other thing which J prefer before thee, yet doſt not thou for all this wholly turne thy ſelfe from me, but thy mercy follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me, if at my time I would returne to thee that I may be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of grace.</p>
               <p>For that thou lookeſt not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, is becauſe I looke not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, but refuſe and contemne thee.</p>
               <p>O infinite pietie, how unhappy is every ſinner that forſaketh thee the fountaine of Life, and ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not thee in thy ſelfe but in that which in it ſelfe is nothing, and ſo had ſtill been if thou hadſt not called it out of nothing? How mad is he who ſeeketh thee that art goodneſſe, and whilſt hee ſeeketh thee goeth back from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:120060:22"/>thee, and turnes away his eyes for every one that ſeeks, ſeekes nothing but good, and hee that ſeeketh good, and goes back from thee, goes back from that which he ſeekes.</p>
               <p>Therefore every ſinner goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray from thee, and wanders far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther off, but when hee returnes to thee thou without delay mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt him, and before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee lookes back to thee, thou with a Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affection caſteth upon him the eyes of thy mercy, neither is thy mercy any thing but thy ſeeing. Therefore thy mercy followeth every man as long as hee liveth whetherſoever he goeth, as thy ſight never forſakes any man. And as long as a man lives thou ceaſeſt not to follow him and by ſweet and internall admonitions to ſtirre him up to ceaſe from his errors, and to be turned to thee that hee may live happily. Thou
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120060:22"/>Lord art the Companion of my pilgramage whitherſoever I goe, thy eyes are alwayes upon mee, And thy ſeeing is thy moving, therefore thou art moved with me, and ceaſeſt not from motion as long as I am moved. If I reſt, thou art with me alſo, if I aſcend thou aſſendeſt if I deſcend thou diſcendeſt, whitherſoever I turne my ſelfe thou art preſent.</p>
               <p>Neither doſt: thou forſake me in the time of tribulation, as oft as I call upon thee thou art neere for to call upon thee is to turne my ſelfe to thee, and thou canſt not be wanting to him that turns himſelfe to thee, neither can any man be turned to thee except firſt thou be preſent, for except thou wert preſent and diddeſt ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licit me. I ſhould not know thee at a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, and then how ſhould I be turned to thee whom I did not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:120060:23"/>know: Thou art therefore my God that ſeeſt all things, And for thee to ſee is to worke, therefore thou workeſt all things, <hi>Not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, therefore O Lord not unto us, but unto thy great name which is</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; doe I ſing eternall glor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for I have nothing that thou doſt not give, neither could I hold that which thou giveſt except thou thy ſelfe dideſt keep it, thou therfore miniſtreſt all things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, thou art the Lord power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and pitifull, which giveſt all things, thou takeſt care of all things, thou art the diſpencer that diſpenceſt, thou preſerveſt all things, And all theſe things doſt thou which art bleſſed for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, work by thy only and moſt ſimple ſight and beholding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:120060:23"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the ſeeing face, to face or the ſeeing of Gods face.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
               <p>RIght gratious Lord and <hi>God,</hi> the longer I looke upon the countenance, the more ſharply it doth ſeeme unto mee that thou bendeſt the edge of thine eyes towards mee. And thy looking upon me makes me conſider how this Image of thy face is therfore thus ſenſibly figurd, becauſe a face could not be painted without co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour nor is colour without quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity: But I ſee not with thoſe fleſhly eyes that beholds this thy Picture, but with the eyes of my minde, and underſtanding the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable truth of thy face which is here repreſented by a contracted ſhadow, which true face of thine is free from all contraction, for it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120060:24"/>is neither ſubject to quantity nor qualitie, nor time nor place being the abſolute forme which is the face of faces.</p>
               <p>When I conſider therfore how that face is the truth and moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equate meaſure of all faces, I am amazed at it for the face which is the truth of all faces is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to quantitie, therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther greater nor leſſe, yet it is not equall to any one becauſe it hath no quantity, but is abſolute and ſuperexalted. It is therefore the truth, which is equality exempt from all quantity. So therefore, I comprehend that thy face, O Lord goes before every face for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable and is the exemplaty truth of all faces, and that all faces are the Images of thy incontractible and imparticipable face.</p>
               <p>Therefore every face that can behold thy face ſees nothing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or diverſe from it ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120060:24"/>cauſe it ſees its own truth, or the truth of it ſelfe. Now the exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h cannot bee other or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, but thoſe things are acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents to the Image in as much as it is not the true examplar; As therefore whilſt I look upon this painted face from the Eaſt, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to looke upon mee, ſo alſo, And in like manner if from the Weſt or South, it ſeemes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to looke upon me, And howſoever I change my face or poſture, the face ſeemes ſtill to be turned towards mee; So is thy face turned to all the faces that behold thee.</p>
               <p>Thy ſight O'Lord is thy face he therefore that beholdeth thee with an amyable face ſhall finde no other, but that thy face looks aymeably upon him, and how much more aymeably he ſhall ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to looke upon thee ſo much more aymeably ſhall he finde thy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:120060:25"/>face towards him: Hee that ſhall look upon thee angerly ſhal like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe finde thy face ſuch towards him, and ſo hee that lookes upon thee cheerfully. For as this fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eye looking through a Redde Glaſſe, or Greene Glaſſe, thinke all it ſees of the ſame colour ſo every eye of the minde that is muffled up in contraction, and paſſion, judgeth thee that art the object of the mind according to the nature of contraction, and paſſion; Man can judge but like a man, for when a man Attributs a face unto thee, he ſeekes not for it, out of the (latitude of the) ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies or nature of men becauſe his judgement is contracted within beneath humane nature, and ſo in judging exceeds not the paſſion of this contraction: So if a Lion ſhould aſcribe thee a face, hee would give thee none but a Lions face, an Oxe an Oxes, an Eagle, an Eagles.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:120060:25"/>
               <p>O Lord how admirable is thy face, which if a young man ſhould conceive, he would imagine it young, if an old man, aged, if a man manly, who could conceive this only examplar or patterne of all faces moſt true, and moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equate to be ſo of all faces, as that it is, nevertheleſſe of every one, and ſo perfectly of every one, as if it were ſo of none other, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he muſt needs out goe and paſſe beyond all formes and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of all formable faces; And how could hee conceive a face, when he muſt tranſcend all faces, and all likeneſſe, and figures of all faces, and al conceptions that can be made of a face, and all Colour, Ornament, and beauty of all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Therefore who ſo faine would ſee thy face, as long as hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives any thing at all is farre from the ſight of it, for every poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible conception of a face is leſſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:120060:26"/>then thy face, O Lord, and every beauty and faireneſſe which can be imagined is leſſe than thy beauty, every other face hath beauty, but is not beauty it ſelfe, but thy face O Lord hath beauty, and this having, it is to be it, there fore it is abſolute beauty, which is the forme that gives, being to every beauteous forme.</p>
               <p>O face moſt comely, whoſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, all things that hath the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſee it are not ſufficient to admire. In all faces is the face of all faces ſeene, but under a veile or covering, &amp; in a dark ſhadow, but revealed not, it is not ſeene untill above all faces, we enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſecret and hidden ſilence, where there is neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge nor conception of a face, for this Miſt Cloud, Darkneſſe, or ignorance, into which the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of thy face enters when hee ſurmounts all knowledge, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:120060:26"/>conception is that beneath which the face cannot be ſeene, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then under a veile, but the miſt it ſelfe reveals that there is thy face above all veiles or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. As our eye, whiles it ſeeks to ſee the light of the Sun which is the face thereof, firſt it beholds it under a veile or Coverture in the Stars in Colours, and in all things that partake the light thereof, but when it ſtrives to ſee it revealedly, and manifeſtly, it tranſcends all viſible light becauſe all ſuch is leſſe than that which he ſeeketh, but becauſe hee would faine ſee the light which hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee, hee knowes this, that as long as hee ſees any thing, it is not that which he would ſee, and conſequently he muſt go beyond all viſible light, &amp; hee that would ſo tranſcend all light that may be ſeene, muſt of neceſſity enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which wants viſible light
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:120060:27"/>which to the eye is (that I may ſo ſay) darkneſſe and when hee is in that darkeneſſe or miſt, then if hee know himſelfe to be in the miſt, he knowes himſelfe now to be come to the face of the Sunne, for from the Excellency of the light of the ſun doth that darknes and miſt in the eye proceed, and by how much he knowes the darkneſſe to be greater, ſo much more truely doth hee in that miſt attaine to the inviſible light, ſo O Lord and no otherwiſe do I ſee the unaproachable light, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſhining of thy face may be without veile or ſhadow approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:120060:27"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>What is the fruit of the Viſion of Gods face, and how it may be had.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 7</head>
               <p>ADmirable is that ſweetneſſe wherewith thou<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> now fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt my Soule O Lord, and ſo great that it muſt needs helpe it ſelfe by all meanes poſſible as well with thoſe things whereof it hath experience in this world, as by thoſe moſt acceptable ſimilitudes which thou inſpireſt. For becauſe thou O Lord art that power and beginning from whence althings, and thy face, that power and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning from whence all faces are, that which they are. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I turne my ſelfe to this great &amp; taull Nut-Tree, and ſeek to ſee the principle or firſt beginning thereof, and I ſee with my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120060:28"/>eye, that it is great tal, broad ſpread, Coloured, loaden with boughs, leaves, and Nutts. Then by the eyes of my minde, I ſee that that Tree was once in the ſeeds, yet not as I now behold it, but virtually or in power, I dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently conſider the wonderfull vertue of that ſeed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in which this whole Tree, and all the nutts, and all the power and vertue of the ſeed of thoſe Nutts, and all the Trees that are potentially in the vertue of the ſeedes of thoſe nuts have bin, and I ſee that that power is not, nor ever wil be in any time that can be meaſured by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Heaven fully explicable, yet that power of the ſeed though inexplicable is but contracted, becauſe it hath no power other than in this particular ſpeces or kinde of Nutts.</p>
               <p>Wherefore though I ſee the Tree in the ſeed, I ſee it only in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:120060:28"/>the contracted power thereof, then doe I conſider O Lord the ſeminarie vertue of all the Trees of divers ſpeces, or ſorts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted unto every ſeveral ſpeces, and in thoſe very ſeeds, I ſee the Trees in power. If therefore I would ſee the abſolute or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted vertue and power of all the vertues of thoſe ſeeds; what the vertue is and what the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple or beginning that gives ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to all ſeeds, I muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity goe beyond all ſeminall vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which can be known or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and enter into that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, wherein there remaines nothing at all of the ſeminall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or vigour, and then in that miſt I finde a moſt ſtupendious power &amp; which no power which can be taught or imagined can approach unto which as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, giving us being to every vertue and power ſeminall, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:120060:29"/>not ſeminall, which abſolute and ſuper exalted vertue and power, ſeeing it gives to every ſeminall vertue, ſuch power as complicates and foulds up in it ſelfe potenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, the Tree and all things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to a ſencible Tree, and which follow the being thereof, certainly then that beginning, and cauſe muſt as a Cauſe have complicitly and abſolutly in it ſelfe, whatſoever it gives to the effect thereof, and ſo I ſee that that virtue and power is the face or Patterne of every arborall face and of every Tree where I ſee that Nut-tree not in its contracted ſeminall vertue, and power, but as in the Cauſe and making power of that ſeminall virtue. And conſequently I ſee the Tree to be a certaine explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſeminall power, and the ſeed a certaine explication of the Almighty power, And I ſee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:120060:29"/>that as the tree in the ſeed is not the tree, but the power of the ſeed, and that the power of the ſeed, is it out of which the Tree is explicated or unſolded, ſo that there is nothing to be found in the Tree which proceeds not from the vertue of the ſeed ſo the ſeminall vertue and power in its cauſe, which is the power of powers, is not the ſeminal power, but abſolute power. And ſo is the Tree in thee my God, thy ſelfe my God, &amp; in thee is it the truth and exemplar or patterne of its owne ſelfe, likewiſe, alſo the ſeed of the Tree in thee is the truth and patterne of it ſelfe both tree and ſeed, thou O God art the truth the patterne or exemplar, and that power of the ſeed which is contracted is the power of the nature of the ſpeces, or fort which is contracted to the ſpeces, and is in it as a contracted beginning
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120060:30"/>But thou O my God art abſolute power, and therefore the nature of all natures.</p>
               <p>O God whither haſt thou brought me that I ſhould ſee thy abſolute face, to bee the naturall face of all nature, the face which is the abſolute Entitie of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the art and knowledge of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing knowable. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſees thy face, ſees all things openly, and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hid unto him, He know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things, he hath all things, O Lord which hath thee, he hath all things that ſeeth thee, for no man ſeeth thee, but hee that hath thee, no man commeth to thee, becauſe thou art unapproachable, no man therefore can take thee, except thou give thy ſelfe unto him, how have I thee O Lord that am not worthy to appeare in thy ſight? How can my prayer come unto thee, that art by any meanes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:120060:30"/>unapproachable? How ſhall I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thee for what is more abſurd then to deſire that thou who art all things in all things ſhouldſt give thy ſelfe unto me, and how wilt thou give thy ſelfe unto me, unleſſe thou give thy ſelfe with all Heaven, and Earth, and all things which are in them.</p>
               <p>Nay how with thou give thy ſelfe unto me, except thou give give thy ſelfe unto me, and while I thus reſt in the ſilence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, thou O Lord anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt within my heart, ſaying be thou thine owne, and J will be thine owne.</p>
               <p>O Lord the ſweetneſſe of all ſweetneſſe, thou haſt placed mee in my Liherty, that I may if I will be mine owne; Hereupon if I he not mine owne, thou art not mine, for then ſhouldeſt thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate libearty, ſeeing thou canſt not be mine, except I be mine
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:120060:31"/>owne. And becauſe thou haſt put this in my liberty, therefore doſt thou not neceſſitate but expect that I ſhould chooſe to be mine owne the fault therefore is in me, not in thee O Lord, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracteſt not thy greateſt goodnes, but powreſt it out moſt plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon all that are capable. And thou O Lord art my goodneſſe, and how ſhall I bee mine owne, except thou O Lord ſhalt teach mee. But this thou teacheſt me, that ſence ſhould obey reaſon, and reaſon beare rule. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſence obey reaſon, I am mine owne, yet hath reaſon nothing to direct her, but thee O Lord which art the word and the reaſon of reaſons.</p>
               <p>Whereupon I now ſee that if I heare thy word which ceaſeth not to ſpeake within me and which ſhineth continually in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I ſhall be mine own free, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:120060:31"/>not the ſervant of Sin, and thou wilt be mine, and give me the ſight of thy face, and then I ſhall be ſafe, bleſſed be thou O God in thy guifts, which only art able to comfort my ſoule, and to erect and quicken it up unto a hope of attaining and enjoying thee, as thine owne gift, and the infinite treaſure of all, deſierable things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>How Gods ſeeing is his loving, Cauſing, Reading, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining all things in himſelfe.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 8.</head>
               <p>REſtleſſe is my heart O God becauſe thy love hath infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it with ſuch a de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re that it cannot reſt but in thee alone. I began to pray the Lords Prayer, and thou inſpiredſt me to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er how then art our Father, Thy
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:120060:32"/>loving is thy ſeeing; thy Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is thy ſeeing which doth ſo fatherly embrace us all, for we ſay Our Father; for thou art the univerſall and ſingular Father: And every one ſaying our Father, implyes that thy Fatherly love comprehends thy Sonnes, all and every one for a Father ſo loves all his Children, that he loves, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, becauſe he is the Father of all, as well as of every one, and loves every one of his Sonnes ſo that every one thinks, himſelfe preferred before all the reſt.</p>
               <p>If therefore thou act a Father, and Our Father, ſurely the love of a Father to his Sonne preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the love of a Sonne to his Father as long as we are thy ſons and looke upon thee as ſoones, thou ceaſeſt not to looke upon us as a Father, therefore thou ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t be our fatherly putveyor ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Fatherly care or us, Thy ſeeing is thy providence.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:120060:32"/>
               <p>If we thy ſounes do abdicate thee Our Father we ceaſe to be ſonnes, nor are we then free ſons in our owne power, but we goe into a farre Country, ſeparating our ſelves from thee, and then we undergoe a grievous ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry under a Prince which is Enemy to thee O God: But thou O Father though for the liberty given us as being the ſonnes of thee which art liberty it ſelfe, thou ſuffer us to goe away and ſpend our liberty, and beſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance after the corrupt deſires of our fences, Yet doſt thou not forſake us utterly, but art pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent continually, ſolliciting us, ſpeaking in us, and calling us back to returne to thee, ready al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to look upon us with the former fatherly eye, if we return and convert to thee.</p>
               <p>O God of pitty look upon me, who being prickt with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:120060:33"/>for the miſerable ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the ſlippery filthineſſe of Swine, where I dyed for hunger, do now returne that I may how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it pleaſeth thee, be fed in thy houſe, feed me with thy ſight O Lord, and teach me how thy ſight ſees all that ſees, and every thing that may be ſeen &amp; every Act of ſeeing, and every ſeeing power, and every power that may be ſeene, and every thing that ariſeth from them, forthy ſeeing is cauſing. Teach me O Lord how at one glance thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveſt them all together, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, when I open the Booke to read, I ſee confuſedly the whole leaſe, and if I will diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh every letter and word, I muſt of neceſſity turne my ſelfe particularly to every one in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I cannot read but one letter after another, and one line after another but thou O Lord lookeſt upon and readeſt all the paper to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:120060:33"/>without any delay of time and if two of us read the ſame thing, one a pace, and the other ſlowly, thou readeſt with both, and ſeemeſt to read in time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou readeſt with them that read and ſeeſt, and readeſt all things together above time.</p>
               <p>Thy ſeeing is thy reading, thou from eternity haſt ſeene and read together beyond al delay of time, all the Bookes which have beene or may be written, and at the ſame inſtant, thou readeſt them ſucceſſively with them that do ſo read them neither doſt thou read one thing in eternity, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them that read in time, but being alwayes the ſame, and after the ſame manner, becauſe thou art not changeable, being fixed Eternity, and eternity in that it forſakes not, time ſeems to be moved with time, a thong indeed motion and eternity is reſt.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:120060:34"/>
               <p>Lord thou ſeeſt and haſt eyes, thou art therefore an eye, becauſe with thee to have is to be, and for this Cauſe in thy ſelfe thou ſeeft all things, for if in me ſeeing were the Eye, as it is in thee my God, then could I ſee all things in my ſelfe, becauſe the eye is of the nature of Glaſſe, and a glaſſe though never ſo little will figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively repreſent a great Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and all things that are in the ſurface thereof, and ſo the ſpecies of all things are in a glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eye, yet becauſe our ſight doth not by meanes of the glaſly eye ſee any thing but that particular whereunto it turnes it ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the power thereof cannot but be particularly determined by the object, therefore it ſeeth not all things that are contained in the Glaſſe of the Eye, but thy ſight being an Eye, or a living Glaſſe ſeeth a l things in it ſelfe,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:120060:34"/>nay being the Cauſe of all viſible things, therefore it containes, and ſees all things in the Cauſe, and reaſon of all things that is in it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Thy eye O Lord proceedeth to all things without turning, our Eye turneth it ſelfe to the object, becauſe our ſight ſees by a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that hath quantity, but the Corner of thy Eye O God hath no quantity, but is infinite being a Circle, nay an infinite Sphere: for thy ſight is an Eye of infinite Sphericity or roundneſſe, and perfection, it ſeeth therefore all things round about and above, and below, O how wonderfull is thy ſight which is (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o all that ſearch for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> How faire and amiable to all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> love thee, How terrible to all that have for ſaken thee O my God: for thou by thy ſight O Lord quick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt every ſpirit, makeſt glad every
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:120060:35"/>one that is bleſſed, and putteſt to flight all ſorrow: looke therefore mercifully upon mee and my ſoule is ſafe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>How the ſight of God is both uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall and Particular, and what is the way thereto</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 9.</head>
               <p>DEare Lord, I cannot but wonder how (ſeeing thou lookeſt upon all, and every one as this painted Image which I behold, figures out unto me) in thy viſive or ſeeing power, the Vniverſall <hi>conicides</hi> with the ſingular: But then I wonder that therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y imagination con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives not how this may be done, becauſe it is in my owne viſive power that I ſeeke for thy Viſion which is not contracted to a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:120060:35"/>Organ as mine is, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am I deceived in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thy ſeeing O Lord is thy offence. If therefore I looke to humanity which is one and ſimple in all men, I finde it both in all and every man, And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in it ſelfe it bee neither Eaſterly, nor Weaſterly, nor Southerly, nor Northerly, yet in Eaſterly men it is in the Eaſt, and in the Weſterly men in the Weſt, and ſo though motion and reſt be not of the eſſence of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, yet it is moved with men that move and reſteth with them that reſt, and it ſtandeth with them that ſtand all together at one and the ſame inſtant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe whether men move or be not moved whether they ſleepe or reſt, humanity forſakes not men. Whereupon if this nature of humanity, which is contracted and no where found without
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:120060:36"/>men; If I ſay that be ſo, that it be not more preſent to one man than another, and be ſo perfectly preſent to one as if it were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to none other, much more deeply then ſhall humanity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contracted (which is the pattern and Idea of this contracted na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and which is as the forme, and the truth of this contracted forme of humanity) never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake humanity contracted in the Individualls, for it is the form which gives being unto the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall nature it ſelfe. Therefore cannot the ſpecificall forme be without it, when as by it ſelfe, it hath no being, for it is from tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is by it ſelfe, before which there is none other.</p>
               <p>Therefore that forme which gives being to the ſpecies, is an abſolute forme, and that art thou O God, which art the former of Heaven; and earth, and all things.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:120060:36"/>
               <p>When therefore I looke to the contracted humanity, &amp; through that to abſolute humanity, that is ſeeing in the contracted the abſolute, as in the effect the cauſe and in the truth the Patterne; then meeteſt thou mee my God as the ſamplar or patterne of all men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and man by himſelfe that is abſolute.</p>
               <p>And when likewiſe in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpecies and kindes I turne my ſelfe to the forme of formes, in all theſe doſt thou occurre, or preſent thy ſelfe, as the Idea or Samplar. And becauſe thou art an abſolute or moſt ſample-ſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar or patterne, thou art not compounded of many Samplars, but art one moſt ſample and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute ſamplar, ſo that of all and every thing that can be formed, thou art the moſt true and ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quat ſamplar. Therefore thou art the eſſence of eſſences<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> giving
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:120060:37"/>to contracted eſſences to be that which they are: for without thee O Lord nothing can be: If then thy eſſence peirce all things, thy ſight muſt needs do ſo too, being thy eſſence.</p>
               <p>As therefore none of the things that are, can flye from their proper being, ſo neither from thy eſſence, which gives, being to the eſſence of al things, and ſo by conſequence not from thy ſight neither. Therefore thou O Lord ſeeſt all thing, and every particular together, and thou art moved withall things that are moved, &amp; ſtandeſt ſtill with all things that ſtand ſtill &amp; in aſmuch as there are things found which are moved, when other things ſtand ſtill, therefore thou O Lord ſtandeſt ſtill, and are moved both at once, for if motion and reſt be both found together at the ſame time, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:120060:37"/>in divers things, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be beſides or without thee, then there is neither mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nor reſt without thee, but unto every one of them all art thou preſent O Lord, together and at once, and to each of them wholly, and yet thou art neither moved nor reſteth, becauſe thou art ſuperexalted and abſolute or free from all thoſe things which can neither be named or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Thou ſtandeſt therefore, and thou goeſt, and yet thou neither ſtandeſt nor goeſt, and that this painted face ſhews mee full well, for if I be moved, the face thereof appeareth to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, becauſe it forſakes me not: And if whilſt I move, another that beholds the face ſtand, ſtill the countenance likewiſe forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not him, but ſtands ſtill with him that ſtands. Yet can it not properly agree to an abſolute
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:120060:38"/>face or ſight that is freed from theſe reſpects, either to ſtand or be moved in that it is above all ſtation or motion, in moſt ſimple and abſolute infinity after or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath which infinity, is motion and reſt, and oppoſition, and whatſoever can be ſaid or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               <p>Whereupon I finde by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, how it is neceſſary for me to enter the miſt, and to admitte the <hi>covicidence</hi> of oppoſites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all capacity of reaſon, and there to ſeek the truth where I meet with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> impoſſibility, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove that the nigheſt intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all aſcent, when I ſhall come to that which is unknowne to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unde ſtanding, and which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry underſtanding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> judgeth far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt off from truth; there art thou O my God which art abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity.</p>
               <p>And by how much more that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:120060:38"/>miſty impoſſibility is known to be more dark, and impoſſible, ſo much the more doth neceſſity ſhine and is the more unvayled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent and drawes neere.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, I thank thee O my God, becauſe thou ſheweſt mee there is no other way of comming unto thee, but that which ſeemeth to all men, even the moſt learned Philoſophers utterly unacceſſible, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, becauſe thou haſt ſhewn mee that thou canſt not elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where be ſeene, than when Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility meets and croſſes me, And thou O Lord which art the food of ſtrong men, haſt anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to do violence to mine owne ſelfe, to beleeve, <hi>becauſe,</hi> Impoſſibility coincident with neceſſitate. And ſo I have found the place where thou wilt revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledly be found, which place is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed with Coincidence of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:120060:39"/>Contradictories, which is the wall of that Paradice wherein thou dwelleſt, whoſe gate is kept by a moſt high ſpirit of reaſon, and if that be not overcome, the entry will not be opened. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Conicideuce of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictories, therefore thou wilt or maieſt bee ſeene, but not on this ſide of it.</p>
               <p>If therefore impoſſibility bee neceſſity in thy ſight O Lord, then there is nothing that thy ſight doth not ſee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>How God is ſeene beyond the coni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidence of contradictories and how ſeeing is being.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 10.</head>
               <p>DRead God, I ſtand before the image of thy face, which I looke upon with my ſencible
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:120060:39"/>eyes, and with my ineternall eyes, I labour to behold that truth which is ſignified in thee, and it comes into my minde O Lord, how thy ſeeing ſpeakes, for thy ſpeaking is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but thy ſight, being they do not really differ in thee, which art abſolute ſimplicity it ſelfe. Then I do clearely finde by experience, that thou ſeeſt all things together, and every thing ſeverally: for I my ſelfe when I Preach at one and the ſame time, ſpeake one word to the whole Church aſſembled together, and to every one that is amongſt them, and in that word which I ſpeake to all, I ſpeak to every one, That which the Church is to mee, that unto thee O Lord is the whole world, and every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Creature that is or can be, ſo therefore thou ſpeakeſt to al, and every one, and thoſe things
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:120060:40"/>to which thou ſpeakeſt, thou ſeeſt O Lord, which art the chiefeſt conſolation of all that truſt in thee, thou inſpireſt me to praiſe thee from the contemplation of my ſelfe, for thou haſt given mee one face as thou pleaſeſt, and that is ſeene generally, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, to all to whom I preach, my owne face is therefore ſeene by all, and my ſimple ſpeech is who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heard by all and every one, but I cannot diſtinctly heare all them ſpeaking together, but one after one: nor diſtinctly ſee them altogether, but one after one, yet if there were in mee ſo great power, that hearing and being heard, ſhold coincident and be all one, and ſeeing, and being ſeene, as alſo ſpeaking, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring (as in thee O Lord which art the Higheſt power) then I could both heare and ſee all at once, and every one in particular
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:120060:40"/>by themſelves, and as I could ſpeak to every one in particular, at once, ſo in the ſame inſtant, while I ſpeake, I could ſee and heare the anſwers of all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one. Now then as being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Doore of the coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of oppoſites, which the Angell keepeth in the entrance of Paradice, I begin to ſee thee O Lord for thou art there where to ſpeake, to heare, to ſee to taſt, to touch, to reaſon, to know, and to underſtand, are all the ſame thing, and where ſeeing coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des which being ſeene and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with being heard, and taſting with being taſted, and touching, with being touched, and ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with hearing, and creating with ſpeaking. If I could ſee as I am viſible or to be ſeene, I were not a Creature, and if thou O Lord ſhouldſt not ſee as thou art to be ſeene, thou wert not God Almighty, thou art Viſible unto
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:120060:41"/>all Creatures, and ſeeſt all for in that thou ſeeſt all, thou art ſeene of all, otherwiſe they could not be Creatures, becauſe by thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they are. And if they ſhould not ſee thee, ſeeing they could not take from thee their being; the being of the Creature is thy ſeeing, and being ſeene.</p>
               <p>Thou ſpeakeſt by thy word to all things that are, and calleſt to bring the things that are not, Thou calleſt therefore that they may heare thee, when they heare thee, then they are, when there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou ſpeakeſt, thou ſpeakeſt to all things, and all things to whom thou ſpeakeſt heare thee. Thou ſpeakeſt to the Earth, and calleſt it to humane nature, and the Earth heareth thee, and its hearing is to be made man Thou ſpeakeſt unto nothing, as if it were ſomething, and nothing heares thee, becauſe it was made ſomething, which was nothing.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:120060:41"/>
               <p>O infinite power, thy concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is to ſpeak, thou conceiveſt Heaven, and it is as thou concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, thou conceiveſt Earth, and it is as thou conceiveſt, while thou conceiveſt, thou ſeeſt, and ſpeakeſt, and workeſt, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can be ſaid. But how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull art thou O my God, thou ſpeakeſt once, thou conceiveſt once, how then art thou althings together, but ſucceſſively many things, how are ſo many divers things from one conception, thou enlightneſt me that am up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Threſhould of the Doore, by telling me that thy concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is moſt ſimple eternity it ſelfe and there is nothing can poſſibly be done after moſt ſimple eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for infinit duration which is eternity it ſelfe, includeth, and comprehendeth all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. Therefore whatſoever appeares unto us in ſucceſſion, is
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:120060:42"/>not after thy conception which is eternity, for thy one and only conception which is thy word, complicates, &amp; infoulds all things, and every perticular, and thy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall word cannot be manifold nor diverſe nor variable, nor changeable, becauſe it is ſimple Eternity.</p>
               <p>So I ſee O Lord, that there is no thing after thy conception, but all things are becauſe thou conceaveſt them and thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaveſt them in Eternitie, and ſucceſſion in Eternitie, is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie it ſelfe without ſucceſſion, even thy word O Lord God: Thou haſt no ſooner conceaved any thing that appeares unto us, temporally than it is: for Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in which thou conceaveſt all temporall ſucceſſion coincides in the ſame now or inſtant of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie nothing can there be paſt or to come, where to come and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:120060:42"/>paſt coincides with the preſent; But that things in this world are according to before and after, is becauſe thou dideſt not before conceave thoſe things that they ſhould bee, if thou hadeſt ſooner conceived them, they had ſooner bin, but in whoſe conception ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there can fall firſt, and later, that hee can firſt conceave one thing, and after another, hee is not Almighty, but becauſe thou art God Almighty thou art with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Walle in Paradice: And that Walle is that Coincidence, where after coincides with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or latter, with firſt where the end coincides with the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, where <hi>Alfa</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> are the ſame.</p>
               <p>Things therefore are alwayes becauſe thou ſpeakeſt that they may be, and they are not before becauſe thou ſpeakeſt not before,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:120060:43"/>and when I read that <hi>Adam</hi> was before ſo many yeares, and that ſuch a one was borne to day, It ſeemes to mee unpoſſible that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould bee then, becauſe thou then wouldſt, and the other borne to day, becauſe thou now wouldſt; And yet thou didſt not will <hi>Adam</hi> to bee ſooner, than thou wouldeſt him that was born to day, but that which ſeems im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible is neceſſity it ſelfe, for now &amp; then are after or beneathe thy word, Therefore they meete with him that comes to thee in the Wall which invirons the place where thou dwelleſt in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicidence; For now and then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicides in the cirele of the Wall of Paradice: But thou my God art and ſpeakeſt beyond now and then, which art abſolute Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:120060:43"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>How in God ſucceſsion of time is ſeene without ſucceſsion.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 12.</head>
               <p>O My God, I have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thy goodnes which art ſo farre from diſpiſing mee a miſerable ſinner, That thou on the other ſide doſt ſweetly feede me with a certain deſire or long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for thou haſt inſpired into mee a moſt welcome ſimilitude, as touching the unitie of the mentall word or conception, and the variety therof in thoſe things that appeare ſucceſſively: For the ſimple conception of a moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Clock leades me a more fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſavoury ſight of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and word, for the ſimple conception of a clocke, compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates or wraps up all temporall
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:120060:44"/>ſucceſſion, And put caſe that a Clocke bee a concep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, then though we heare the ſound of the 6th houre, before the 7th yet the 7th is not heard but when the concep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion commands, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is 6th ſooner in conception, then the 7th or 8th but in the ſimple conception of a Clocke, there is no houre before or after another, although the Clock ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtrike but when the concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bids: And it may be truely ſaid when the Clocke ſtrikes ſix, that then the Clocke ſtrikes ſix; becauſe the conception of the Maſter wil have it ſo and becauſe a Clock in the conception of <hi>God</hi> is a conception, it may a little ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare how ſucceſſion in a Clocke is without ſucceſſion in a word or conception and how in that moſt ſimple conception are folded up all motions and founds, and whatſoever we find in ſucceſſion,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:120060:44"/>and that whatſoever happens ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively doth not by any meanes exceed the conception, but is an explication of the conception be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the conception gives being to every thing: And that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing is ſooner than it comes to paſſe becauſe it was not ſooner conceaved than it might be; Suppoſe then a conception of a Clocke to be Eternity, and then the motion in the Clocke is to be ſucceſſion, therefore eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doth both, infold, and unfold ſucceſſion, for the conception of a Clock which is Eternity; doth both complicate and explicate all things.</p>
               <p>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſed bee thou therefore O Lord my God. which feedeſt and nouriſheſt me with the milke of ſimilitudes, untill thou give mee ſtronger meat: Lead me O Lord God by theſe pathes to thee, for except thou lead me, I ſhall ſaint
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:120060:45"/>by the way, becauſe of the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my corruptible nature, and the fooliſh Veſſell which I beare about mee: I returne againe in conifidence of thy help, O Lord to finde thee beyond the wall of confidence, complication, and explication, and as I goe in and out by this door of thy word and conception, I finde moſt ſweete paſture and foode, when I finde thee explicating thy power, I goe out, when I find thee both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating, and explicating; I goe in and out, I goe in from the Creatures, to thee thou Creator, from the effect to the cauſe, I go out from the Creator to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, from the cauſe to the effect, I goe both in and out together, when I ſee how going out is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, and going in at the ſame inſtant going out, As hee that numbreth doth at the ſame time, both explicate and complicate, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:120060:45"/>the power of unity, and complicate number into unitie. For the creatures going out from thee, is for thee to enter into the Creature, and to explicate is to complicate, And when I ſee thee God in Paradice, incompaſſed there within the wall of the coni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of contraries, I ſee that thou doſt neither complicate nor explicate disjunctively nor copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively; For disjunction and communion are both a like, the wall of connifidence, beyond which thou art abſolute and free from all that can be either ſaid or thought.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:120060:46"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>That where the inviſible is ſeene, the uncreated is created.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 12.</head>
               <p>CRown of my joy and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thou haſt appeared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, ſomtimes as inviſible from every creature becauſe thou art a God ſecret and hidden, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and infinite is incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible by any manner of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, Then thou appearedſt to mee as viſible to all things, for every thing is ſo far forth as thou ſeeſt it: and that could not bee in act; except it did ſee thee, for viſion gives being, becauſe it is thy Eſſence; So thou my God art viſible, and inviſible thou art, inviſible as thou art, and thou art viſible as the creature is, which
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:120060:46"/>ſo farre forth is as it ſees thee, by every thing that ſees, in every thing that may be ſeene, and in every act of ſeeing art thou ſeen, which art inviſible, and abſolute, and free from all ſuch things, and infinitely ſuperexalted; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O Lord I muſt leap over the Wall of inviſible viſion where thou art found; and the Wall is all things, and nothing both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and thou which meeteſt or appeareſt to us as though thou wert all things, and nothing at al both together, dwelleſt within that high Wall which no wit can by its own power ever be able to climbe.</p>
               <p>Sometimes thou appeareſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee, ſo that I imagine thou ſeeſt all things in thy ſelfe, like a living Glaſſe, in which all things ſhine, and becauſe thy ſeeing is thy knowing, then it comes into my minde that thou doſt not ſee
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:120060:47"/>alſo things in thy ſelfe as in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Glaſſe, for then thy know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg ſhould ariſe from the things: Sometimes thou preſenteſt thy ſelfe to mee, that thou ſeeſt all things in thy ſelfe, as power or vertue, by looking upon it ſelfe, As the power or poſſibility of the ſeed of a Tree, if it ſhould looke into and behold it ſelfe, would in it ſelfe ſee the Tree in power; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the vertue of the ſeede is potentially the Tree, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, me thinkes that thou doſt not ſee thy ſelfe, and all things in thy ſelfe, as power or poſſibility, for to ſee a Tree in the power of the vertue, differs from that viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by which the Tree is ſeene in act, and then I finde how thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite vertue or power is beyond all ſpecular and ſeminall vertue, and beyond the conicidence, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation or reflection of the cauſe, and alſo the thing cauſed, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:120060:47"/>that that abſolute vertue is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute viſion, which is perfection it ſelfe, above all manner of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for all the manners which explaine the perfection of ſeeing are without any manners, thy Viſion which is thy Eſſence, O my God.</p>
               <p>But ſuffer moſt mercifull Lord that I thy vild Creature may yet ſpeake unto thee; If thy ſeeing be thy creating, and thou ſeeſt nothing but thy ſelfe, but thy ſelfe art the object of thy ſelfe, (for thou art both the thing ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and the things ſeene, and the act of ſeeing, how then doſt thou creat other things from thee, for thou ſeemeſt to creat thy ſelfe as thou ſeeſt thy ſelfe, But thou comforteſt mee O life of my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for although I meet with the wall of abſurdity, which is of the Conicidence of creating and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing created, as though it were
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:120060:48"/>impoſſible that creating and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing created ſhould coincide (for to admit this, ſeemes to be as if one ſhould affirme, that a thing is before it is, for when it creates it is, and becauſe it is created it is not) yet it hinders not, for thy creating is thy being, neither is it any other things at once to create, and to be created, than to communicate thy being unto all things, that thou maieſt bee all things in all things, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine abſolute from all things, for to call to being things that are not, is to communicate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to nothing, ſo to call is to create, to communicate is to bee created. And beyond this Coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidence of creating and being created, act thou God abſolute and infinite, neither creating nor in poſſibility of being created, although they are all that they are becauſe thou art.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:120060:48"/>
               <p>O thou heights of riches, how incomprehenſible art thou, as long as I conceive a Creator, creating, I am yet on this ſide the wall of Paradice, ſo as long as I conceive a Creator in poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of being created, I have not yet entred, but am in the wall, but when I ſee thee as abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute infinite, whereunto neither the name of a Creator creating, nor of a Creator in poſſibility of being created can agree, then I beginne to ſee thee revealedly, and to enter into the Garden of delights, becauſe thou art no ſuch thing as can be ſaid, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but infinitly and abſolutly ſuper-exalted above all ſuch things. Thou art not therfore on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Creator, but infinitly more then a Creator, though with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee nothing is done, or can be done: To thee bee praiſe and glory for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:120060:49"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>That God is ſeene abſolute infinite.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 13.</head>
               <p>THou Lord God, thou helpe of them that ſeeke thee, I ſee thee in the Garden of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and I know not what I ſee, for <hi>I</hi> ſee nothing viſible, only this I know, that I know not what I ſee, nor ever can know it, name thee I cannot, becauſe I know not what thou art; And if any man ſay thou art named by this or that name, in as much as he nameth thee, I know that it is not thy name, for every terme of the manner of ſignifications of name is a Wall, beyond which I fee thee.</p>
               <p>And if any man expreſſe any conception, by which thou mayſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:120060:49"/>be conceived, I know that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception is not the conception of thee, for every conception is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in the Wall of Paradiſe, And if any man expreſſe any ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, and ſay that according thereunto thou art to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. I know likewiſe that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude is nor thyne, ſoe if any man declare any underſtanding of thee, as though hee would give a meanes to underſtand thee, this man is yet farre from thee, for from all theſe, art thou ſeperated by a moſt high Wall: This Wall ſeperates thee from all things that can bee ſaid or thought, for thou art abſolute from all things that can fall into any mans conception, Therefore when I am higheſt of all lifted up, then I ſee thee infinity, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore art thou inacceſſible, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, unnameable, unmul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipliable, and inviſible, and ſo hee
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:120060:50"/>that will aſcend to thee muſt get up above every terme and end and things, finite. But how ſhall he come unto thee, the end whereat hee aimeth, if hee muſt aſſend above the end, Hee that mounts up above the end, doth he not enter into that which is indeterminate, and confuſed and ſo inregard of the underſtanding, into ignorance and obſcurity, which are intellectuall confuſion; The underſtanding muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore become ignorant, and bee placed in the ſhadow if it would ſee thee, But O my God what is this ignorance of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, is it not a learned igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, therefore canſt not thou O God be approached unto, as being infinite, but by him whoſe underſtanding, is in ignorance, and namely ſuch a one as knows himſelfe to be ignorant of thee, How can the underſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:120060:50"/>thee which art infinitie; The underſtanding knowes it ſelfe ignorant, and that thou canſt not be conceived, becauſe thou art Infinitie. For to underſtand Infinitie, is to comprehend that which is incomprehenſible.</p>
               <p>The underſtanding knowes it ſelfe ignorant of thee, becauſe it knows thou canſt not be known, unleſſe that which is unknowable be known, and the inviſible ſeen, or the inacceſſible approached unto. Thou my God art abſolute Infinitie, which I ſee to be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite end, but I can not conceive how an end ſhould bee an end without an end. Thou O God art the end of thy ſelfe, becauſe thou art whatſoever thou haſt, if thou haſt an end thou art an end, Thou art therefore an infinite end becauſe thou art the end of thy ſelf, for thy end is thy eſſence, the eſſence of the end is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:120060:51"/>or limited in another end, but in it ſelfe, the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which is the end or bound of it ſelfe is infinite. And every end which is not the end of it ſelfe is a finite end, thou O Lord becauſe thou art the bound that boundeſt all things, therefore art thou the end or bound wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is no end or bound, and ſo the bound without bound, or infinite bound which paſſeth all reaſon, for it foulds a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
               <p>When therefore I affirme a boundleſſe bound or an infinite end, I admit darkneſſe to belight, ignorance, knoledge, and that which is impoſſible to be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary or of neceſſity; And becauſe we admit that there is a bound of that which is bounded, wee muſt neceſſarily admit of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite or laſt end or bound with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out abound, but we cannot but
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:120060:51"/>admit infinite being, therefore we cannot but admit the infinite Conſequently we admit the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incidence of contraries, above which is the infinite. And that Coincidence is a contradiction without a contradiction, as an end without end.</p>
               <p>And thou O Lord ſaiſt unto me that as alterity in unity is without alterity, becauſe it is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſo contradiction in Infinitie is without contradiction, becauſe Infinitie. Infinitie is ſimplicity it ſelfe, but contradiction cannot be without alterity, yet alterity inſimplicity is without alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe it is ſimplicity, for all things that are ſaid are affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of abſolute ſimplicitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide or are the ſame with it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there to have, is to be, the oppoſition of oppoſites, is their oppoſition without oppoſition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the end or bond of things infinit
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:120060:52"/>is no end or bound without end or bound.</p>
               <p>Thou therefore O God art the oppoſition of oppoſites, becauſe thou art infinite, and becauſe thou art infinite, thou art infinite it ſelfe: In infinity is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of oppoſites without oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
               <p>O Lord my God, the ſtrength of the weake, I ſee thee to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity it ſelfe, therefore to thee, there is nothing other or diverſe or contrary, and adverſe for hee that is infinite doth not ſuffer with himſelfe any alterity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (being infinity) there is no thing beſides or without it, for abſolute infinite, includes and invirons all things. Therefore if there were infinite and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beſides it, it were not infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite nor any thing elſe, for infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite cannot be either greater or leſſe, therefore thereis nothing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:120060:52"/>beſides or beyond it, for if infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie did not, include within it ſelfe al being it were not infinite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And if there were no infinite, then were there no end or bound nor alteritie, nor diverſitie, which without alterity of bands and termes cannot be Infinite, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being taken away, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth nothing, there is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore infinitie, and it complicates all things, as nothing can be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it, and hereupon here is nothing other, or diverſe unto it, Infinitie therefore is ſo all things that it is none of them all.</p>
               <p>To Infinity therefore, there can no name agree, for every name may have a contrary, but to unnameable Infinitie, there can be nothing contrary, neither is Infinitie the whole, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is oppoſed a part, nor can it be a part, nor can Infinitie be great,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:120060:53"/>or little, nor any thing which can be named, neither in heaven or in earth, above all theſe is Infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Infinitie is to nothing either great or leſſe or equall.</p>
               <p>But while I conſider Infinitie neither to be greater nor leſſe to any thing imaginable, I ſay it is the meaſure of all things being neither greater nor leſſe. And ſo I conceive it the equalitie of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſuch an equality is Infinitie, yet is it not ſo equalitie, as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality oppoſed unto it, but there equalitie is inequalitie, for ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie in Infinitie is without inequalitie becauſe it is Infinite, ſo equality in Infinity is infinity, Infinity equality, is an end with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end; whereupon though it be neither greater nor leſſe, yet is it not equality, as contracted equality is underſtood, but it is infinite equality, which is not capable of more or leſſe, and ſo it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:120060:53"/>is not more equall to one then to another, but ſo equall to one that to all, and ſo to all that to none of all, for that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite is not contractable, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines abſolute, if it were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractable by Infinity, it were not infinite: It is not therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractable to the equality of the finite although it be not equall to any thing, for how ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality agree with the infinite, whereunto agreeth neither more nor leſſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore that which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, is neither greater nor leſſe, nor inequall to any thing ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, and yet it is not, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore equall to that which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, becauſe it is above every finite thing, to wit, by it ſelfe, that which is infinite then is it utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abſolute, and incontractable.</p>
               <p>How high art thou O Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things and with all how
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:120060:54"/>humble, becauſe in all things: If infinitie were contractible to any thing nominable, as a line, or a ſurface, or a ſpecies, or kinde, it would draw to it ſelfe that whereunto it were contracted, and it implies that the infinitie ſhould bee conttactible, for it ſhould not be contracted, but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract; for if I ſay that the infinite is contracted to a Line, as when I ſay an infinite Line, then is the Line attracted or drawne to that which is infinitie, for a line cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to be a line when it hath no quantite or end, an infinite line is not a line, but a line in infinite is infinite: And as nothing can be added to that which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, ſo the infinite cannot bee contracted unto any thing, to make it other then infinite, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodneſſe is not goodneſſe but infinite, infinite quantitie is not quantity but infinity, and ſo in all things.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:120060:54"/>
               <p>Thou art a great God of whoſe greatneſſe there is no end; and therefore I ſee thee, the unmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable meaſure of all things, as the infinite end of all things.</p>
               <p>Thou art therefore O Lord without beginning and end, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe infinite, thou art the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning without beginning, and the end without end, and ſo the beginning that the end, and ſo the end that the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ginning, and neither beginning nor end, but above them both even abſolute, Infinitie it ſelfe bleſſed for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:120060:55"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>How God complicateth or infol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all things without alterity.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP 14.</head>
               <p>O Lord God by the infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy mercy I ſee thou art infinitie incompaſſing all things. There is therefore nothing without thee, but all things in thee, nothing that is another thing from thee: Thou teacheſt me O Lord how alteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is not in thee, is not likewiſe in it ſelfe, neither can it be, nor doth that alterity which is not in thee, cauſe that one Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is different from another, although indeed one be not the other, for the Heaven is not the Earth, though it be true that the Heaven is the Heaven, and the Earth the Earth.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:120060:55"/>
               <p>If I therefore ſeeke for alteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which is neither within thee nor without thee, where ſhall I finde it, and if there be no ſuch thing, how then is the earth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creature then the heavens, for without alteritie this cannot be conceived, but thou ſpeakeſt in me O Lord and ſaiſt that of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity there is no poſitive prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple or beginning, and ſo it is not for how ſhould alterity be without beginning, except it ſelfe were a beginning, and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; But alterity is not the principle of being, for it is called alterity of not being, for becauſe one thing is not another, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is called <hi>Alterum</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, alterity therefore cannnt be the principle of being, becauſe it is ſo called from not being, neither hath it principle of being when it is not from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:120060:56"/>
               <p>Therefore is not alteritie any thing but that Heaven is not Earth, it is becauſe Heaven is not infinite it ſelfe which containeth all being.</p>
               <p>Whereupon becauſe infinitie is abſolute infinitie, it comes to paſſe that one thing cannot bee another.</p>
               <p>As the being of <hi>Socrates,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth all the being of <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> in which ſimple being of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> there is not alterity or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, for the being of <hi>Socrates,</hi> is the individuall unity of all things that are in <hi>Socrates,</hi> ſo that in that one being is complicated the being of all things which are in <hi>Socrates,</hi> namely in the very individuall ſimplicitie, where there is nothing found other, or divers: But in that one and only being all things which have any being belonging to <hi>Socrates</hi> are, and are explicated, and without
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:120060:56"/>or beſides it, they neither are nor can be, although withall in that moſt ſimple being, the eye bee not the eare, nor the head the heart, and the ſeeing is not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieg, nor ſence reaſon, nor doth this happen out of any principle of alterity, but preſuppoſing the moſt ſimple being of <hi>Socrates</hi> it comes to paſſe that the head is not the feet, becauſe the head is not the moſt ſimple being of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> And therefore the being thereof doth not include the whole being of <hi>Socrates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo I ſee (thou O Lord gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me light) that becauſe the ſimple being of <hi>Socrates</hi> is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether incommunicable, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contractable to the being of any Member whatſoever, therefore the being of one Member is not the being of another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that moſt ſimple being of <hi>Socrates,</hi> is the being of all the Members of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:120060:57"/>
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> in which all the variety and alteritie of being which is in the Members is ſimple unity, as the plurality of the formes of the parts is unity in thy forme of the whole, ſo it is in ſome ſort O God betweene thy being which is abſolutly infinity, and all thoſe things that are, abſolut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I ſay, as the abſolute forme of being of all contracted formes. Thence it is that the hand of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> being ſeparated from his body, though after it be cut off, it be not any more the hand of <hi>Socrates,</hi> yet it remaines ſtill in ſome being of Carkaſſe, and that is becauſe the forme of <hi>Socrates</hi> which gives being, doth not give being ſimply, but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracte d being, namely the being of <hi>Socrates,</hi> from which the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the hand is ſeparable, and yet may remaine under another forme, but if the hand were once
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:120060:57"/>wholly ſeparated from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contracted, being which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and abſolute, it would alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ceaſe to bee, brcauſe it were then ſeparated from all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>I thanke thee O Lord my God, who as far as I am able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave largely, ſheweſt me how thou art Infinitie it ſelfe, compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating and infolding the being of all things in moſt ſimpl power which were not infinite, except infinitly united, for power uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted is the ſtronger. Therefore that power which is ſo united that it cannot be more, is infinite and omnipotent. Thou art God Almighty, becauſe abſolute ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, which is abſolute infinity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:120060:58"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>That actuall Infinitie is unitie, in which the figure is Veritie.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 15.</head>
               <p>REgard thy ſervant in mercy, Lord, though he be a foole, ſave from what thou granteſt, that he may ſpeak unto thee his God.</p>
               <p>I ſee it this painted face the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Infinitie, for the ſight is indeterminate either to object or place, and ſo infinite, for it is not more turned to one then to another of them that looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, And although the ſight thereof be in it ſelfe infinite, yet it ſeemes to bee terminated by every one that lookes upon it, becauſe it looks upon every one that lookes upon it ſo determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:120060:58"/>as though it lookes on him alone and nothing elſe.</p>
               <p>Thou ſeemeſt therefore unto me O Lord as poſſibility and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſolute and infinite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable and determinable by every forme for me, for we ſay that the formable poſſibility of the matter is infinite, becauſe it can never be finiſhed, but thou anſwerſt in mee, O infinite light that abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power, or poſſibilitie is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelfe, which is beyond the Wall of coincidence, where poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of being made Coincides with poſſibility of making where power coincides with Act matter although it be in power to infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite formes, yet it cannot have them all at once actually, but the power is terminated by one, and that removed by another. If there fore the <hi>(poſſe eſſe)</hi> may be, of the matter ſhould coincide with the Act, it would ſo be power that it
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:120060:59"/>would be act alſo, and as it was in power to infinite formed, ſo it would be actually formed infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely. Now Infinitie in act is without alteritie, and it cannot be infinitie, but it muſt be unitie, There can not therefore be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite formes in Act, but actuall infinity is unity. Thou therefore O God which art infinite it ſelfe, art thy ſelfe, one God, in which I ſee all may be is in act, for poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility abſolute or free from all power contracted to matter or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paſſive power whatſoever is abſolute being, for whatſoever is in infinite being is the moſt ſimple infinite it ſelfe, ſo to may be all things in the infinite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the infinite being it ſelfe, likewiſe alſo actually to bee all things in the infinite is the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite being it ſelfe; Wherefore the abſolute may be, and the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute being in Act in thee my
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:120060:59"/>God are nothing but thou my infinite God, thou my God art all may be.</p>
               <p>The may be of the matter is materiall, and ſo contracted, and not abſolute, ſo the ſenſible and rationall may be is contracted, but to bee altogether uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted coincides with ſimply ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, that is infinite.</p>
               <p>When therefore thou my God appeareſt unto me as matter for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable, becauſe thou receiveſt the forme of every one that beholds thee, then thou lifteſt me up to ſee how he that looks upon thee, doth not give thee forme, but in thee hee beholds himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe from thee hee receives that which hee is. And ſo what thou ſeemeſt to receive from the beholder, that thou giveſt as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the living glaſſe of eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is the forme of formes; In which glaſſe whilſt one lookes
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:120060:60"/>hee ſees his owne forme, in the forme of formes, which is the glaſſe, and judgeth the forme which hee ſees in that glas to be the figure of his forme, becauſe it is ſo in materiall polliſt glaſſe, though the contrary thereof be true, becauſe, that which hee ſees in the Glaſſe of eternity, is not the figure but the truth of that which himſelfe (the beholder) is the figure. The figure therefore in thee in God is truth and the ſamplar or patterne of all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that is or may be.</p>
               <p>O God which art wonderfull to every underſtanding, thou ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt ſometimes as if thou wert a ſhadow, and thou art light, For when I ſee how according to my Change the ſight of thy Picture ſeemes changed, thy face alſo ſeemes changed, becauſe thou appeareſt to me changed as if thou werſt the ſhadow that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:120060:60"/>the alteration of him that walketh. But becauſe I am the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhadow, and thou the truth, I judge by the change of the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow that the truth is changed. Thou therefore O my God art the ſhadow, but ſo that, thou art the truth alſo, thou art the image of me, and of every thing, but ſo that thou art the exemplar and patterne alſo.</p>
               <p>O Lord God the enlightner of hearts, my face is a true face, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou that art the truth haſt given it me, My face is alſo an Image, becauſe it is not the truth it ſelfe, but the Image of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute truth, therefore I do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate and infold in my concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the truth and the Image of my face, and I ſee that in it the Image coincides with the faciall truth, ſo that in as much as an Image in ſo much it, it true. And then thou ſhewed me O Lord,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:120060:61"/>how according to the mutation of my face, thy face is both chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and unchanged, changed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it forſakes not the truth of my face, unchanged becauſe it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not the change of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: Wherefore as thy face forſakes not the truth of my face, ſo it followes not the changing of an alterable Image, for abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute truth is unalterability, the truth of my face is mutable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo, the truth that it is alſo the Image, but thine is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, becauſe it is ſo an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage that it is alſo the truth; Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Truth cannot forſake the truth of my face, for if it ſhould forſake it my face which is mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, truth could not ſubſiſt.</p>
               <p>So doſt thou ſeeme to mee O God (becauſe of thine infinite goodneſſe) immutable, becauſe thou forſakeſt not the mutable Creature, but becauſe thou art
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:120060:61"/>abſolute goodneſſe thou art not mutable, becauſe thou doſt not follow mutability, and thy moſt performed depth O God that doſt not forſake, and withall doſt not follow the Creatures: O inexplicable piety that offereſt thy ſelf to him that beholds thee, as if thou tookeſt being from him, and comforteſt thy ſelfe to him that hee may love thee the more, by how more like to him thou art, for we cannot hate our ſelves, therefore we love that which participates and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies our being, and wee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace our likeneſſe, becauſe we are repreſented in the Image in which we love our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe O God as our Creature out of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of thine infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſo thou mayſt draw us unto thee, for thou doſt draw us to thee by all meanes poſſible, that a free reaſonable Creature
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:120060:62"/>can be drawne by. And in thee O God Creating Coincides, which being created, for the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage which ſeemes to be Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by me is the truth that crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth mee, that ſo at length I may underſtand how much I ought to be bound unto thee, when in thee loving, and being coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, for if I ought to love my ſelfe in thee my ſimilitude, and then be eſpecially bound unto it when I ſee thee love mee as thy Creature, and Image, how can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not that father love his ſonne, who is ſo a Sonne, that he is a Father alſo, And if he be much to be loved which is a ſonne in eſtimation and a father in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, art not thou moſt of all which in eſtimation exceedeſt a ſonne, and in knowledge a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Thou God wouldeſt that filiall love ſhould conſiſt in eſtimation
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:120060:62"/>and thou wilt be eſteemed liker then a ſonne, and be knowne more intimate then a Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art love, complicating and infolding, aſwell filiall, as paternall delection. Be thou therefore which art my ſweeteſt love, my God bleſſed for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>That God except hee were infinite could not be the end of our deſires.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 16.</head>
               <p>O My God the fire ceaſeth not to burne, nor more doth the love of deſire which is carried towards thee, which art every deſirable forme, and that truth which in every deſire is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, wherefore ſince I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun from thy melliflous gift to taſt thy incomprehenſible
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:120060:63"/>ſweetneſſe, which the more infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite it appeares is ſo much the more welcombe unto me, I ſee that for this cauſe thou O God art unknowne to all Creatures that in this moſt ſacred igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as in an in unmeaſurable, and inexhauſtible treaſure, they may have the greater reſt, for much more joyfull is hee that findes ſuch a treaſure as hee knowes is utterly innumerable and infinite, then hee that findes ſuch a treaſure as is but finite, and may be numbred. Hereupon this moſt ſacred ignorance of thy greatneſſe is the moſt deſired and longed for food of my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, eſpecially when I finde ſuch a treaſure in my field, and therefore the treaſure is mine owne. O fountaine of riches thou wilt bee comprehended in my poſſeſſion &amp; yet remaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible and infinite, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:120060:63"/>thou art the treaſure of delights, whereof no man can deſire an end, how ſhould the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite deſire not being, for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the will deſire not being the appetite cannot reſt but is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into Infinitie.</p>
               <p>Thou deſcendeſt O Lord that thou maiſt be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, thou remaineſt inunnume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and infinite, and dideſt thou not remaine infinite thou couldſt not be the end of the deſire, for the intellectuall deſire is not carried to that which can bee greater or more deſireable; But every thing on this ſide, the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite may be greater, therefore the end of the deſire is infinite; Thou then O God art infinitie it ſelfe, which alone I deſire in all my deſires, and the knowledge whereof I can come no nearer than to know that it is infinite. By how much more incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:120060:64"/>therefore I may compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend thee my God, ſo much more do I attaine unto thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I do the more attaine the end of my deſire, whatſoever therefore I meete withall that labours not to ſhew thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, that I caſt away, becauſe it ſeduceth me.</p>
               <p>My deſire then is in that which leads me to thee, becauſe it ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth away all that is finite and comprehenſible, for in theſe it cannot reſt, being by thy ſelfe led unto thee, as the beginning without beginning, and the end without end. Therefore is my deſire led by the eternall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (from whom it hath that it is a deſire) to the end without end and that is infinite; That I therefore a poore man ſhould not be contracted with thee my God, if I had knowne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible proceeds from
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:120060:64"/>hence, becauſe I am led by thee unto thy ſelfe incomprehenſible and infinite.</p>
               <p>I ſee thee O Lord my God in a certaine mentall rapture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if the ſight be not ſatisfied with ſeeing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor the Eare with hearing, then much leſſe is the underſtanding with underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: Therefore that which it underſtandeth, doth not ſatisfie the underſtanding, neither is it the end thereof nor can that (on the other ſide) ſatisfie it which it underſtandeth not at all but only that which it underſtandeth in not underſtanding, for that intelligible which it knoweth, doth not ſatisfie nor that which it knoweth doth not ſatisfie, nor that which it knoweth not all but that which it knowes ſo intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, that it can never bee fully underſtood, that only can ſatisfy. As hee that hath an inſatiable
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:120060:65"/>hunger cannot be ſatisfied with a little meate, nor with that meat (though never ſo much) that he cannot come at, but only with that meate which hee can both come at, and which though hee continual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſwallow, yet can it never be all ſwallowed, being ſuch as in ſwallowing is not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed becauſe it is infinite.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>That God cannot perfectly bee ſeene except he be ſeene unitrine, or one in three.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 17.</head>
               <p>FAire and amyable haſt thou ſhewne thy ſelfe unto me O God that more thou canſt not be, for thou art infinitly lovely O my God therefore thou canſt never be loved by any thing as thou art worthy of love but by
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:120060:65"/>an infinite lover, for except there were an infinite lover, thou wert not infinitly amiable, for thy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miableneſſe which is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of being infinitely lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, is becauſe there is a poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of loving infinitely, from which, and the poſſibility of being infinitely loved arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth an infinite Bound of love of the infinite lover, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite amiable, and is not multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable.</p>
               <p>Thou therefore O my God which art love, art the love, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and the love amiable, and the love which is bond of the love loving, &amp; the love amiable, I ſee in thee my God a love loving, and a love amiable: And in that I ſee in thee a 1. loving love and an 2. amiable love, I ſee the 3. bond of either love, and this is nothing elſe but what I ſee in thy abſolute unity, in which I ſee a
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:120060:66"/>unitie uniting a unity that may be united, and the union of both: And whatſoever I ſee in thee my God that thou art, Thou art therefore that infinite love which without the loving, and the amiable, the Bond of both cannot to me ſeeme na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and perfect love, for how can I conceive the moſt perfect and naturall love without the loving, and the amiable and the union of both, for that love ſhould be loving and amiable, and the bond of both: I finde is contracted love that it is of the eſſence of perfect love, And that which is of the eſſence of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect contracted love, cannot bee wanting to abſolute love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from whence contracted love hath all its perfection, and how much more ſimple love is, ſo much the more perfect, but thou my God art moſt perfect, and ſimple love
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:120060:66"/>therefore thou art to moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ſimple, and naturall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of love, for hence it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that in thee being love, three is not one thing that loves, and another that is loved, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is the Bond of love, but the ſame even thou thy ſelfe, O my God, becauſe therefore in thee the lovely coincides with the loved, <hi>and it is all</hi> one to bee loved, and to love, certainly the bond of Coincidence is an eſſentiall Bond, for there is nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n thee which is not the eſſence it ſelfe: Therefore they which ſeeme unto me to be three name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the loving, the lovely, and the Bond are the moſt ſimple abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute eſſence, therefore they are not three but one.</p>
               <p>That eſſence of thine O my God which appeares unto me to be moſt ſimple, and (that I may ſo ſay) moſt one is not moſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:120060:67"/>naturall and moſt perfect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the things before named.</p>
               <p>The eſſence therefore is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fould, and yet there are not three things in it, becauſe it is moſt ſimple. The plurality therefore of the three forenamed is ſo a plurality, that it is nevertheleſſe a unity, and ſo is the unity a u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it is alſo a plurality, the plurality of three is a plurality without a plural number, for a plural number cannot be a ſimple unity becauſe it is a plurall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: There is therefore no nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merall diſtinction of the three, becauſe that is eſſentiall, one number being eſſentially diſtinct from another, And becauſe the unity is Tryne, it is not a unity of the ſingular number, for the unity of the ſingular number is not Trine.</p>
               <p>O moſt wonderfull God, which neither art of the ſingular
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:120060:67"/>nor plurall number, but above all plurality and ſingularity, one in three, and three in one: I ſee therefore in the Walls of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, where thou my God art, plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality coincide with ſingularity, and that thou dwelleſt farre farre beyond that.</p>
               <p>Teach me O Lord how I may conceive that poſſible which I ſee to be of neceſſity, for there meets an impoſſibility that the plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of three without which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive thee to be perfect, and naturall love is a plurality without number, As hee that ſayes one, one, one, thrice ſayes thrice one and yet hee ſayes not three but one, and this one thrice one hee cannot ſay thrice without three, although hee ſay not three, for when he ſaies one thrice, he repeats the ſame, and doth not number for to number is to altar one, but to repeat one
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:120060:68"/>and the ſame thrice, as to plurifie without number. Therefore that plurality which I ſee in my God, is an alterality without alterity, becauſe it is an alterity which is Identitie.</p>
               <p>For when I ſee the loving is not the lovely, and that the bond is neither the loving nor the lovely, yet do I not ſo ſee the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not to bee the lovely, as though the loving were one and the loving, the lovely and the Bond. There is therefore one love, without the which none of the three could be, I am one which am the loving, I am the ſame which am the lovely, and I likewiſe am all one which am the Bond arriſing from the love wherewith I love my ſelfe, and yet I am one and not three things.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe then that my love be my eſſence as it is in my God,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:120060:68"/>then in the unity of my eſſence, there would be the unity of the three foreſaid, and in the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the three foreſaid unity of eſſence, and they would bee all in my eſſence contractedly after the manner that I ſee them to be in thee truely and abſolutely, yet for all that love, loving would not be love lovely, nor the bond, and that I finde by this practiſe and experiment.</p>
               <p>For by love loving which I beare to another thing without my ſelfe, as it were to an extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall lovely, there followeth a Bond of my eſſence whereby I am bound to that thing as much as in me lyeth, which thing is not joyned to be by that Bond, becauſe paradventure it loves me not, whereupon though I love it ſo that my loving, love extends it ſelfe upon it, yet my loving love doth not draw with it or to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:120060:69"/>it my lovely love, for I am not lovely to it, for it cares not for me, though I love it extreamely, as the Sun ſometimes cares not for his Mother though ſhee love him never ſo tenderly. And ſo I finde by experience that love loving is neither love lovely, nor the Bond, but I ſee the loving is diſtinguiſhed from the lovely and the Bond, which diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction nevertheleſſe is not in the Eſſence of love becauſe I cannot love either my ſelfe or any thing, elſe beſides my ſelfe without love, ſo love is of the eſſence of all the three; And ſo I ſee that the eſſence of thoſe three fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid is moſt ſimple though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves they bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct.</p>
               <p>I have in a ſimilitude O Lord expreſſed ſome manner of fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſte of thy nature, but mercifully ſpare mee for attemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:120060:69"/>out the unfigurable taſt of thy ſweetnes, for if the ſweetnes of an unknowne Apple be unfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurable by any Picture or figure, and unexpreſſible by all words, who am I miſerble ſinner that go about to ſhew thee that art unſhewable, to figure the viſible that art inviſible, and to offer or preſent to the taſt that infinite and utterly in expreſſible ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thine which I never yet deſerved to taſt, and by thoſe things which I expreſſe, I rather make it appeale little than great, But ſo great is thy goodneſſe O my God that thou ſuffereſt even the blinde men to ſpeak of light, and to ſet forth the praiſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, of which notwithſtanding they neither do nor can know a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that can bee revealed unto them: But Revelation goes not ſo farre as taſt, the eare of faith reacheth not that ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:120060:70"/>which is utterly untaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. And this thou haſt revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to me O Lord, that the Eare hath not heard, nor hath it ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the heart of man the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitneſſe of thy ſweetnes which thou haſt prepared for them that love thee; This thy great Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath revealed unto us, which was raviſhed beyond the Wall of Coincidence into Paradice, where only thou that art the fountaine of delights, canſt be revealedly ſeene, I have laboured to ſubject my ſelfe to a rapture, truſting to thine infinite goodneſſe, that I might ſee thee that art inviſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale an unreveleable viſion, and how far I have gone thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, but I know not: howſoever ſufficient for mee is thy grace whereby thou aſſureſt me thou art incomprehenſible, and erecteſt me to a firme hope that thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:120060:70"/>my guide, I ſhall at length come to the fruition of thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>That unleſſe God were trine or three in one, hee were not felicity.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP 18.</head>
               <p>DId all men open the eyes of their minde, which they have by thy gift O Lord attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they might ſee with me how thou a jealous God becauſe love loving canſt hate nothing, for in thy ſelfe a lovely God, thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicateſt all things lovely, thou loveſt every loving thing that ſo they might ſee as I doe, by what bond or league thou art united unto all things. Thou O Lord inlargeſt thy love unto all men, and loveſt ſo all things in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, that withall thou loveſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing in particular, But many
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:120060:71"/>are they that do not love thee, becauſe they prefer ſomething before thee. But if love lovely were not diſtinct from love lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, thou wouldeſt be ſo lovely unto all men, that they could love nothing beſides thee and all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſpirits would be neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to the love of thee. But thou art ſo noble O my God, that thou wilt have it in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of reaſonable ſoules whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will love thee or no, wherefore upon thy loving it followeth not that thou art lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>Thou therefore O my God, art by the bond of love united unto al things, becauſe houſprea deſt abroad thy love upon every Creature of thine, but every ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall ſpirit is not united unto thee, becauſe it beſtowes not its love upon thy lovelineſſe, but upon ſome other thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:120060:71"/>unto it is united and knit.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt eſpouſed every rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoule by thy loving love, but not every ſpouſe loveth thee her husband, but for the moſt part ſome other whereunto ſhe cleaveth, but how could the ſoule of man thy ſpouſe O my God, attaine thy end except thou wert lovely that ſo by loving thee that art lovely, ſhee might reach the bond and moſt happie union.</p>
               <p>Who therefore can deny thee to be God, three in one, when hee ſees that thou wert neither a noble naturall nor perfect God, nor his ſpirit had free will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor himſelfe could come to the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thee and his owne happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe except thou wert three and one.</p>
               <p>For becauſe thou art the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that underſtandeth, the underſtanding intelligible,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:120060:72"/>and the Bond of both, therefore the underſtanding created may attaine in thee its intelligible God, union with thee, and felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. So being thou art the love lovely, the created loving will, may in thee its lovely God at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine union and felicity, for hee that receiveth thee God the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable receptible light, may come to ſuch a union of thee that he may be united to thee as a Sun to his Father.</p>
               <p>I ſee O God by thy illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that a reaſonable nature cannot attaine to a union with thee, but becauſe thou artaminable and intelligible, wherefore mans nature is not poſſible to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thee a loving God (for ſo thou art not his object) but hee may bee united to thee as his lovely God, becauſe that which is lovely is the object of that which loveth, So in like manner that
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:120060:72"/>which may be underſtood is the object of the underſtanding, and wee call that the truth which is the object.</p>
               <p>Wherefore thou my God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art the intelligible truth, the created underſtanding may be united unto thee, and ſo I ſee that mans reaſonable na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be united only to thy divine and amiable nature, and that man receiving thee the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible God, paſſeth into that Bond which may for the ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof bee called by the name of filiation or ſonne-ſhip, for then the Bond of filiation we know no ſtricter. And if this Bond of union be the greateſt, then which a greater cannot be, this muſt needs come to paſſe, becauſe if thou the lovely God canſt be more beloved by a man, then is that Bond come to the moſt perfect filiation, that, that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:120060:73"/>filiation may be perfection com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating all poſſible filiation, by which all ſonnes do attaine their laſt felicity and perfection. In which higheſt ſonne filiation is as Art in the Maſter, or the light in the Sunne, but in others as Art in the Schollars or light in the Starrs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>How Ieſus is the union of God and Man.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 19.</head>
               <p>I Give unſpeakeable thanks to thee my God, the life and light of my ſoule, for now I ſee the faith which by the Revelation of the Appoſtles the Catholike Church holdeth namely how thou a loving God begetteſt of thy ſelfe a lovely God and that thou the lovely begotten God att the abſolute Mediator, for
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:120060:73"/>by thee is every thing that is or can be, for thou the willing or loving God in thy ſelfe the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God complicateſt all things, for every thing that thou O God willeſt, or conceiveſt is complicated in thee the lovely God, for there cannot bee any thing except thou will it to be: All things therefore in thy love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conception have their cauſe or reaſon of being, neither is there any other cauſe of all things, but becauſe it ſo pleaſeth thee, nothing pleaſeth the lover, as a lover, but the lovely; Thou therefore a lovely God art the Son of God a loving father, for in thee is all the complaiſance of the Father. So all being crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table is complicated in thee the lovely God.</p>
               <p>Thou therefore a loving God, when as of thee is a lovely God, as the Sonne of the Father in as
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:120060:74"/>much as thou art God the loving Father, of God thy lovely Son; art the Father of all things that are for thy conception is thy Sonne, and all things in him, and thy union, and thy conception, is the Act and operation ariſing, in which is the act and explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things; as therefore of thee the loving God, is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated the lovely God which Generation is conception, So from thee the loving God, and thy lovely conception begotten by thee, proceeds thy act, and thy conception which is the knot knitting, and the God uniting thee, and thy conception, as to love unites the loving, and the lovely in love, and this knot is called the ſpirit for the ſpirit is as motion proceeding from the mover and the moveable: conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently motion is the explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the conception of the mover.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:120060:74"/>
               <p>All things therefore are to be exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icated in thee, God the holy Ghoſt, as they are conceived in thee God the ſonne.</p>
               <p>I ſee then becauſe thou God doſt ſo enlighten me, how all things in thee God the ſonne are God the Fathers as in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, conception, cauſe or ſamplar, and have the ſonne is the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um of all things as the reaſon or forme, for by the mediation of reaſon and wiſdome, thou God the Father workeſt all things, and the ſpirit or motion puts the conception of reaſon in effect, as we finde by experience, that the Arke in minde of the Artificer, is put in effect by the mediation of the motive power which is in the hands; Then I ſee O my God thy Son is the medium or mean of the union of all things, that all things by the mediation of thy Son may reſt in thee.</p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:120060:75"/>
               <p>And I ſee bleſſed Ieſus, the ſon of man moſt Highly united to thy ſon, and that the ſon of man could not be united to thee God the Father, but by mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy ſon, the abſolute Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator.</p>
               <p>Who is not moſt highly ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed that doth attentively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe things. Thou my God openeſt unto mee wretch, ſuch a ſecret that I ſee man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not underſtand thee the Father, but in thy ſon which is intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, and the Mediator, and that to underſtand thee is to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto thee. Man may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be united unto thee by thy ſon which is the meane of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and humane nature moſt highly united unto thee in what man ſoever in be cannot be more united to the meane, then it is united, for without the medium it cannot be united unto thee.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:120060:75"/>
               <p>It is therefore moſt united to the meane, yet it is not made the meane; whereupon though it cannot be made the meane, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it cannot be united unto thee without a meane, yet it is ſo joyned to the abſolute meane, that betweene it and the ſonne who is the abſolute meane, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can mediate, for if any thing could mediate betweene mans nature, and the abſolute meane, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en were it not moſt highly or abſolutely united un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee.</p>
               <p>O good Jeſus, I ſee in thee mans nature to be moſt highly joyned to God the Father by the higheſt union, even a greater then by which it is joyned to God, the ſonne the abſolute Mediator.</p>
               <p>Therefore humane filiation, becauſe thou art the ſon of man is in thee Jeſus moſt highly uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the divine filiation, that
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:120060:76"/>thou art worthily and truly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Son of God and man, for in thee nothing mediates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Son of man, and the Son of God.</p>
               <p>In the abſolute filiation which is the Son of God is complicated all filiation, whereunto thy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane filiation O Jeſus is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peramely united, therefore thy humane filiation ſubſiſts in thy divine, not only complicitly, but as the attracted in the attracting, and the united in the uniting, and the ſubſtantiated in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiating.</p>
               <p>Therefore in thee O Jeſus there is no poſſible ſeparation of the Son of man from the Son of God, for ſeparability is where the union might be greater, but where the union cannot be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nothing can mediate: ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore can have no place where nothing can mediate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:120060:76"/>the things united, and where the united ſubſiſts not in the uniting the union is not the higheſt, for there is a greater u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion where the united ſubſiſts in the uniting, then where the united ſubſiſts a part, for ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the greateſt remoteneſſe from union.</p>
               <p>So I ſee in thee my Ieſus how humane fiiation by which thou art the ſon of man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſubſiſts in the divine filiation by which thou art the Sonne of God, as in the greateſt union, the united with the uniting; To thee O God be glory for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:120060:77"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Jeſus is underſtood the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of the divine and humane nature.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP 20.</head>
               <p>VEry clearely doſt thou ſhew unto me O never fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling light, that that greateſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion whereby mans nature in thee Ieſus is united unto the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature, is not by any means like to an infinite union, for the union by which thou O God the Father art united unto God thy ſon is God the holy Ghoſt, and therefore an infinite union, for it reacheth unto abſolute eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Identitie, but it is not ſo where the humane nature is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the divine, for the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature cannot paſſe into an eſſentiall union, which the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine as that which is finite canot
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:120060:77"/>be infinitly united to that which infinite, for then it would paſſe into the Identitie of the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and ſo it would ceaſe to be finite, when the infinite were verified of it. Wherefore this u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion by which the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is united unto the divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is nothing elſe but an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of the humane nature to the Divine in the higheſt degree, ſo that the humane nature whilſt ſuch cannot be attracted any higher:</p>
               <p>It is therefore the greateſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his humane nature (as humane) to the divine, becauſe there can be no greater, but it is ſimply the greateſt, not infinite as the divine union.</p>
               <p>I ſee therefore by the benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of thy grace in thee Ieſus the ſon of man, the ſon of God, and in the ſon of God I ſee the Father; for in thee the ſunne of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:120060:78"/>man I ſee the Son of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art ſo the ſon of man that thou art alſo the ſon of God and in the finite attracted na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I ſee the infinite attracting nature, I ſee in the abſolute Son the abſolute father, for the Son as Son cannot bee ſeene unleſſe the father be ſeene, I ſee in thee Ieſus a divine filiation, or ſonne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which is the truth of all fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and likewiſe a moſt high human filiation which is the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt image of abſolute filiation.</p>
               <p>As therefore the Image be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene which and the Patterne or ſamplar there cannot mediate a perfect image, doſt moſt neere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubſiſt in the truth of that whoſe Image it is, ſo do I ſee thy humane nature ſubſiſting in the divine nature: Therefore I ſee all things in thy humane nature, which I ſee in thy divine. But I ſee them after an humane man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:120060:78"/>in thy humane nature, which are the divine truth it ſelfe in the divine nature.</p>
               <p>Thoſe things which I ſee in thee after a humane manner O Jeſus, are the ſimilitude of the divine nature, but a ſimilitude is without a meane joyned to the Patterne or ſamplar, ſo that a more like can neither be nor be imagined in the humane or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable nature, I ſee are ſonable humane ſpirit moſt ſtrictly uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the divine ſpirit, which is abſolute reaſon, and ſo the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane underſtanding, to the divine underſtanding and all things in thy underſtanding O Jeſus, for thou O Ieſus as God underſtandeſt all things as God, and this underſtanding is to bee all things; Thou underſtandeſt all things as man, and this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is to be the ſimilitude of all things, for a thing is not
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:120060:79"/>underſtood by a man but in a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude a ſtone is not in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of a man as its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cauſe or reaſon, but as in its ſpecies or ſimilitude.</p>
               <p>In thee therefore O Ieſus the humane underſtanding is united to the divine, as the moſt perfect image to the truth of the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern. As if then I ſhould conſider the Ideall forme of an Arke in the minde of the Artificer, and the ſpecies of an Arke made moſt perfectly, and according to the Idea by the Maſter himſelfe, how then the Ideall forme is the truth of the ſpecies, and united unto it as the truth unto the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in one Maſter. So in thee O Ieſus the Mr. of Maſters, I ſee the abſolute Idea of all things, and the ſimilitudinarie ſpecies of the ſame moſt highly united, I ſee thee O good Ieſus within the Wall of Paradice becauſe
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:120060:79"/>thy underſtanding is both the Truth and the Image, and thou art both God and a Creature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity and finite. And it is not poſſible thou ſhouldeſt be ſeene on this ſide the Wall, for thou art the coup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of the divine creating nature with the humane created nature.</p>
               <p>And I ſee this difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thy humane underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and any other mans, that no one man knoweth all things, which may be knowne by man, becauſe no mans underſtanding is ſo joyned to the ſamplar of all things as the ſimilitude to the truth, but that it might be more neerely joyned and ſet more in act<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not ſo many things, but that he might underſtand more by his acceſſe unto the ſamplar of things, from whence every thing that is an act hath actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:120060:80"/>But thy underſtanding doth actually underſtand all things that are intelligible by man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in thee humane nature is moſt perfect and moſt joyned to its ſamplar or Pattern, for which union thy humane underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding exceeds every created un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darſtanding in the perfection of underſtanding; Therefore all reaſonable ſpirits are far beneath thee of all whom thou O Ieſu art the Maſter and the light and thou art the perfection and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all things, and by thee as by the Mediator, they came unto the abſolute truth, for thou art both the way unto the truth, and the truth it ſelfe, then art both the way unto the life of the underſtanding, and the life it ſelfe; Thou art the odour of the food of gladneſſe, and alſo the taſte that maketh glad: Be thou therefore O ſweet Ieſu, bleſſed for ever more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:120060:80"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>That without Jeſus therei is no poſſible felicity.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP 21.</head>
               <p>IEſu the end of all, in whom as in the laſt of their perfection all Creatures reſt thou art utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unknowne to all the wiſe men of this world; becauſe of thee we affirme contradictories to be moſt true, thou being both the Creator and the Creature, the attracting, and the attracted the finite and alſo the infinite, they ſay it is folly to beleeve this poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, They flye thy name there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and receive not that light wherewith thou haſt enlightned us, but thinking themſelves wiſe, they continue fooles, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and blinde for ever, But if they would beleeve that thou Chriſt, God and man, and would
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:120060:81"/>receive and entertain the words of the Goſpell, as the words of ſo great a Maſter, then would they clearly ſee that all things in compariſon of that light, that there is hid in the ſimplicity of thy words, are moſt thick and palpable darknes and ignorance; Therefore only the little ones that beleeve do obataine this moſt gratious and quickening Revelation, for there is hid in thy moſt ſacred Goſpell which is the heavenly food, all deſireable ſweetneſſe, which cannot be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted but by him that beleeveth and eateth. And if any man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and receive it, hee ſhall finde it moſt true by experience that thou cameſt downe from Heaven, and art the only Maſter of truth.</p>
               <p>O good Ieſu thou art the tree of lif in the Paradice of delights for no man can be fed with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:120060:81"/>life but from thy fruit, Thou O Ieſu art the forbidden food to all the ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> which being expulſed out of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, doth ſeek their living in the earth in which they labour.</p>
               <p>It behoveth every one there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to put off the old man of preſumption, and put on the new man of humility which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy ſelfe, if he hope ever to taſt of the food of life within the Paradice of delights.</p>
               <p>There is a nature of the new and old <hi>Adam,</hi> but it is in the old <hi>Adam</hi> animall, and in the new <hi>Adam</hi> ſpirituall, becauſe in thee Ieſus, it is united to God which is a ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Every man therefore muſt as by humane nature common to him and thee, ſo in one ſpirit be united to thee O Ieſus, that ſo in his nature which is common to thee O Ieſus, hee may come to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:120060:82"/>God the father which is in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice.</p>
               <p>To ſee God the Father there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and Ieſus Chriſt his Son is to be in Paradice and
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Glory,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioy,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> everlaſting, becauſe hee that is without Paradice cannot have ſuch a viſion, ſeeing neither God the Father nor thou O Ieſus art to be found without Paradice, every man therefore hath attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned felicity which is united to thee O Ieſus, as a member to the head, no man can come to the Father except hee be drawne by the Father.</p>
               <p>Thy Father therefore O Ieſus drew thy humanity by his Son, and by thee O Ieſus the Father deaweth all men.</p>
               <p>As therefore thy manhood O Ieſus is united to the ſon of God the Father, as to a meane by which the Father drew it, ſo eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:120060:82"/>mans humanity is united un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee O Ieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, as to the only meane by which the Father drawes all men. Thou art there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Ieſu, without whom it is impoſſible that any man ſhould attaine felicity, Thou art O Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, the Revelation of the Father, for the Father is inviſible to all men, and only viſible to his Son, and next thee to him who ſhall by thee and thy Revelation bee found worthy to ſee him.</p>
               <p>Thou art therefore hee that uniteſt every bleſſed man, and every bleſſed man ſubſiſteth in thee as the united with the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
               <p>Not one of the wiſe men of this world is capable of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe not knowing thee.</p>
               <p>No happie man can ſee the Father but with thee O Ieſus within Paradice. Of the happie contradictories are verified as
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:120060:83"/>of thee O Ieſus, ſeeing he is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto thee in a reaſonable na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and one ſpirit: for every happy ſpirit ſubſiſts in thine, as the quickned in thee quickning, Every happy ſpirit ſees the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible God, &amp; in thee O Ieſus is united unto the unapproachable and immortall God, and ſo in thee the infinite is united to the Infinite, and the incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible is comprehended by eternall fruition which is the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant felicity that can never bee waſted nor ſpent; have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me O Ieſus, have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me and grant that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealedly ſee thee, and then my ſoule is ſafe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:120060:83"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Ieſus ſeeeth and worketh.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 22.</head>
               <p>Never can the eye of the minde be ſatisfied with the ſight of thee O Ieſus, becauſe thou art the compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment and fulnes of all mentall beauty.</p>
               <p>And in this Picture I gueſſe at the wonderfull and ſtupendious ſight: O more then bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Ieſus, for thou Ieſus whilſt thou didſt walke in this ſenſible world, didſt uſe fleſhly eyes like unto us, for with them no otherwiſe than we do, thou dideſt ſee one thing and one thing, for there was in thine eyes, a certaine ſpirit which was the forme of the Organ, as the ſenſible ſoule in the body of a living wight. In that ſpirit there was a noble diſcretive or diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:120060:84"/>power, by which O Lord thou didſt clearely and diſtinctly ſee this thing coloured thus, and that other thing otherwiſe; And more highly yet by the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of the face, and eyes of the men thou ſaweſt, thou waſt a true Iudge of the Paſſions of the ſoule anger, gladneſſe, ſorrow, and yet more ſubtilly by a few ſignes didſt thou comprehend that which lay hid in the minde of man, for there is nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the minde which is not in ſome ſort ſignified in the face, and principally in the eyes (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Meſſengers of the heart) for in all theſe Iudicia or ſignes, thou didſt much more truely reach the inwards of the ſoule, than any created ſpirit, for from ſome one though very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mal ſigne thou didſt ſee the whole concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a man, as underſtanding
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:120060:84"/>men do by a few words ſee through a long preconceived ſpeech, which is to be explicated at length, and as well learned men if they caſt their eyes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo little upon a booke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are able to recite the whole intent of the writer as though they had read it through: In this kinde of ſeeing thou O Ieſus didſt far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell all the perfection, ſwiftneſſe, and ſharpnes of all men paſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and to come and yet this viſion was but humane, which was not done without a Carnall eye, nevertheleſſe it was ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and admirable, for if there be men found that by long and ſubtill diſcuſſion are able to dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher any Carracter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to read the minde of the writer in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters and ſignes then newly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and never ſeene before, thou O Ieſus didſt certainly ſee all things under every ſigne and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:120060:85"/>figure. If it be read that there was ſometimes a man found which by whatſoever ſignes of the eye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw the thought of him that asked him, although hee ſang ſome verſe or meeter in his minde: Much better O Ieſus didſt thou apprehend and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand every conception by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry motion of the eye. My ſelfe ſaw a deafe Woman which by the motion of her Daughters lippes which ſhee ſaw did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what ſoever ſhee ſaid aſwell as if ſhee had heard her. If this by long cuſtome be thus poſſible in them that are deafe and dumbe, and the Religious which ſpeake to one another in ſignes, much more perfectly didſt thou O Ieſu which didſt actually know whatſoever was to be known as a Mr. of Maſters, give judgement true and in fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible of the heart and its concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:120060:85"/>in the leaſt and to us invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible becks, and nods, or ſignes.</p>
               <p>But to this thy humane and moſt perfect viſion though infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and contracted to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, was the abſolute and infinite viſion united, by which viſion as God, thou ſaweſt all things and every thing at once aſwell abſent as preſent, aſwell paſt as to come.</p>
               <p>Thou therefore O Ieſus didſt by thy humane eye ſee viſible accidents, but by thy abſolute di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſight the ſubſtance of things. Never any man beſides thee O Ieſus ſaw the ſubſtance or quoditie of things whileſt hee was in the fleſh. Thou only didſt truely ſee the ſoule and the ſpirit and whatſoever was in man: For as in man the intellective power is united to the animall viſive power, ſo that man ſees not only as a living Wight, but alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes and judges of a man. So
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:120060:86"/>abſolute ſeeing was in the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus united to the humane intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall power which is diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or deſcerning in the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall ſight.</p>
               <p>The animall viſive power in man ſubſiſts not in it ſelfe, but in the reaſonable ſoule as in the forme of the whole, ſo the viſible intellectuall power ſubſiſts not i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it ſelfe, but in thee O Ieſus th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abſolute viſive power. O thy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable ſight moſt ſweet Ieſus, we finde ſome times by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences how with our eye wee ſee ſomebody paſſing by, but becauſe wee took no heed to diſcerne who it was, we cannot tell him that asketh us the name of him that paſſeth by, though we know him well enough, and knew there was ſome body paſſed by; Wee did ſee him, therefore animally but not humanely, or wee ſaw him as we were living wights,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:120060:86"/>but not as we were men, becauſe we did not apply our diſcretive, or diſcerning power: By which we finde that the nature of the powers, although they be united in the one forme of a man; yet they remaine diſtinct, and have diſtinct operations. So in thee O Ieſus I ſee after a certaine like manner the humane intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all nature united to the divine nature, and that accordingly as man thou didſt many things, and as God many wonderfull things above man.</p>
               <p>I ſee O moſt mercifull Ieſus the intellectuall nature in reſpect of the ſencible abſolute, and not as the ſencible is finite, and tyed to the Organ as the ſenſible vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive power is tyed to the eye, but unproportionably more abſolute is the divine power above the intellectuall: For the humane underſtanding to the end it may
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:120060:87"/>be but unto act, hath neede of phantaſmata or appearances in the phantaſie, and they cannot be had without ſences, and ſences ſubſiſt not without a body, and therefore the power of humane underſtanding is contracted and ſmall needing the aforeſaid things. But the divine under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is neceſſity it ſelfe, not depending nor needing any thing but all things need it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which they cannot be. I do more attentively conſider how there is one diſcurſive power which by reaſoning diſcourſeth and ſeeketh, and another which judgeth and underſtandeth, for we ſee a Dog diſcourſe and ſeeke his Maſter and diſcerne him, and heare his calling, and this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is in the nature of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malitie in the degree of the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificall perfection of a Dogge, and there are yet other living
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:120060:87"/>wights found of a more cleare diſcourſe according to the more perfect ſpecies or kinde, and this diſcourſe in man comes neereſt to the intellectuall power that it may bee the ſupreamneſſe of ſenſible perfection containing under the intellectuall, many and innumerable degrees of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the ſpecies or kindes of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wights do make plaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, for there is no ſpecies or kinde which hath not the degree of perfection proper unto it ſelfe, and moreover every one of the degrees hath its latitude within the which we ſee the individuals of the ſpecies pertake it diverſly, But the intellectuall nature in like manner under the Divine, hath innumerable degrees of ſenſible perfection; ſo in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature are complicated all degrees of intellectuall perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of ſenſible likewiſe, and all
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:120060:88"/>other things. So in thee my Ieſus I ſee all perfection, for being moſt perfect man I ſe in thee the underſtanding united to the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or diſcurſive power which is the ſupreamneſſe of the ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power. And ſo I ſee the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in reaſon as the thing placed in its place, as a Candle in the Chamber which enlightens the Chamber, and all the Walls and the whole buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding yet according to the degree of diſtance more or leſſe.</p>
               <p>I ſee next the divine word united to the underſtanding in its ſupreameneſſe, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding it ſelfe to the place where the word is received as we finde in our ſelves the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to be the place where the word of the Mr. is received, as if the light of the Sun ſhould be joyned with the aforeſaid Candle.</p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:120060:88"/>
               <p>For the word of God illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nateth the underſtanding as the light of the Sun doth this world.</p>
               <p>In thee therefore my Ieſus I ſee the ſenſible life illuminated by that intellectuall light: I ſee the intellectuall life to be a light enlightning and enlightned; and I ſee the divine life illuminating or enlightning only; For I ſee the fountaine of light in that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall light, to wit the word of God, which is the truth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting every underſtanding; thou therefore art only the light of all Creatures becauſe thou art ſo a creature that thou art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the bleſſed Creator.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:120060:89"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Jeſus dyed and yet the Vnion with life remained.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP 23.</head>
               <p>IEſus the moſt ſavorie food of the minde how admirable doſt thou appeare unto mee when I behold thee within the Wall of Paradice? for thou art the word of God humanified and man dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and yet thou art not as it were compounded of God and man. For amongſt thoſe things that compound, proportion is neceſſary without which there can be no compoſition, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene finite and infinite there is no proportion: Nor art thou the confidence of the Creature
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:120060:89"/>and the Creator in ſuch ſort as the Coincidence makes one thing to be another, for the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature is not the Divine, nor contrary wiſe, for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature is not changable or alterable into another nature being eternity it ſelfe, nor doth any nature whatſoever, becauſe of its union to the divine nature pas into another nature, as when the Image is united to its truth for it cannot then be ſaid to bee altered, but rather to goe backe from its alterity, becauſe it is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited unto its proper truth which is inalterability it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Nor canſt thou O ſweet Jeſu be ſaid to be a middle nature, betweene divine and humane, when as betweene them there cannot be any middle nature partaking of both, for the divine nature is not partakeable, being wholly abſolutely moſt ſimple:
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:120060:90"/>Nor couldſt thou then O bleſſed Ieſus be either God or man.</p>
               <p>But I ſee thee O Lord Ieſus, one ſuppoſition above all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, becauſe thou art one Chriſt after the ſame manner that I ſee thy one human ſoule in which as in the ſoule of any man, I ſee there was a corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible ſenſible nature, which did ſubſiſt in an incorruptible intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall nature.</p>
               <p>Nor yet was that ſoule com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of corruptible and in corruptible, neither did the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſoule coinſide with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall, but I ſee an intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall ſoule to be united to the body by a ſenſible power, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the body; And if the intellectuall ſoule ſhould ceaſe to Quicken and Enlighten the Body though it were not ſeparated from the body, yet would that man be dead, becauſe
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:120060:90"/>his life would ceaſe, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the body were not ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from life, being the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is the life thereof. As when a man intellectually la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and ſeeks by the meanes of his ſight to diſcerne one that is comming, and yet being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with other conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, his attention ceaſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that inquirie though his eyes be ſtill faſtened upon it, his eye is not ſeparated from the Soule, though it bee ſeparated from the diſcretive or diſcerning attention of the Soule. But if that rapture ſhould not only ceaſe from the diſcretive quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but alſo from the ſenſitive quickening that eye were dead, becauſe it were not quickened: Yet for all that it were not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the intellective forme which is the form giving being: As a dry hand is united to the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:120060:91"/>forme which unites the whole body.</p>
               <p>There are ſound men as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> relates, which can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract or draw back the vivifying ſpirit, and ſo they appeare dead and feele nothing, ſuppoſing it to be ſo.</p>
               <p>In this cloſe, the intellectuall nature would remaine united to the body, which body would not be under any other forme than it was before, nay it would have the ſame forme and remaine the ſame body, neither would the quickening force ceaſe to be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but would remaine in union with the intellectuall nature, although actually it did not extend it ſelfe into the body, I ſee that man tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dead becauſe hee wants the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vifying life (for death is the want of the quickner) and yet that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy would not be dead ſeparated from the life which is the Soule
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:120060:91"/>thereof. After the ſame manner moſt mercifull Ieſus, I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold abſolute life which is God inſeparably united to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane underſtanding, and by it into the body, for that union is ſuch a one that a greater cannot be, and a ſeparable union is much inferior to ſuch a union as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be greater: Therefore it was never true, nor ever ſhall be that thy divine nature was ſeparated from thy humane, conſequently neither from the ſoule nor the body, which are thoſe things without which humane nature cannot be, although it bee moſt true that thy Soule ceaſed to quicken thy body, and that thou didſt truly ſuffer death, and yet waſt never ſeparated from the truth of life.</p>
               <p>If that Prieſt whom Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> mentions had whatſoever power it were to take vivificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:120060:92"/>out of his body by drawing it up unto the ſoule, as if a candle that enlighteneth a Chamber were alive and ſhould draw up thoſe beames by which it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightens the Chamber into the Center of its light, and its draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up were nothing but a cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to inflame; what marvell is it if thou Ieſus being the moſt free and living light haſt power to lay downe, and to take up thy quickinnig ſoule, and when thou wouldeſt take it up thou ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edeſt death, and when thou wouldſt reſume it by thine owne thou didſt riſe againe.</p>
               <p>Now an intellectuall nature is called a humane ſoule when it quickens or animates a body. And the ſoule is ſaid to be taken away when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ane underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ceaſeth to quicken, for when the underſtanding ceaſeth from the Office of quickening
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:120060:92"/>and in this reſpect ſeparateth it ſelfe from the body, it is not therefore ſimply ſeparated.</p>
               <p>Theſe things thou inſpireſt o Ieſus that thou mighteſt ſhew thy ſelfe to moſt unworthy mee, as far as I am capable, and that I may in thee contemplate that mortall humane nature hath put on immortality, that all men of the ſame humane nature may in thee attaine reſurrection and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine life.</p>
               <p>What then can bee ſweeter, what more pleaſant then to know this, that in thee O Ieſu we finde all things that are in our nature, which only canſt do all things and giveſt moſt liberally and up, bradeſt no man. O inexpreſible mercy and pity, thou God which art goodneſſe it ſelfe couldſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſatisfie thy infinite clemency and bounty except thou gaveſt us thy ſelfe: Neither could this be don
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:120060:93"/>more conveniently for us that are the receivers then that thou ſhouldeſt aſſume our nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we could not approach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thine, ſo thou cameſt to us and art named Ieſus the Saviour bleſſed for evermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>How Ieſus is the word of life.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 24.</head>
               <p>THy gift, thy beſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt guift inables me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templat thee my Jeſus preaching the words of life and bounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſowing the Divine ſeeds in the hearts of the hearers, And I ſee them go away which rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not the things of the ſpirit: But I ſee thy Diſciples abiding it which began to taſt the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that Doctrine which, quickneth the ſoule, for all whom
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:120060:93"/>that firſt and chiefeſt of all the Appoſtls <hi>Peter</hi> confeſt that thou Ieſus hadſt the word of life, and wondered that they which ſeeke life would go from thee: <hi>Paul</hi> heard from thee Ieſus in a rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the words of life, and then neither ſword nor famine of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſeparate him from thee: No man could ever forake thee that had taſted the words of life who can ſeparate a Beare from Hony, after hee hath once taſted the ſweetneſſe of it; How great is the ſweetneſſe of truth, how moſt delectable a life doth it give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all bodily ſweetneſſe, for it is abſolute ſweetneſſe, from whence floweth all that by any taſt is deſired: What is ſtronger than love by which every lovely thing hath to bee loved? If the knot or Bond of contracted love be ſometimes ſo great that the feare of death cannot breake it,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:120060:94"/>what a knot is there of that love raſted from whence is all love? I wonder not that all cruelty of paines was accounted nothing by other of thy Souldiers of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, to whom thou gaveſt thy ſelfe, the life to be taſted afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand.</p>
               <p>O Jeſus my love, thou haſt ſowed the ſeed of life in the field of beleevers, and watered it with the teſtimoney of thy blood, and ſhewed by bodily death, <hi>that truth is the life of the reaſonable ſpirit,</hi> the ſeed grew in the good ground and brought forth good fruit, thou ſheweſt me O Lord how my ſoule is the breath of life in regard of my body into which it breatheth and infloweth life, And it is not in regard of thee O God, but as it were a power or poſſibility of life: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou canſt not but grant the things that are asked, if they
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:120060:94"/>be asked with a moſt attentive faith, thou infloweſt or inſpireſt me that there is in a Child a ſoule which hath a vegetative power and force in act, for the Childe groweth; It hath likewiſe a ſencitive power in act, for the Childe feeleth, it hath likewiſe an imaginative power, but not yet act, it hath likewiſe a diſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive power, whoſe act is yet more diſtant; And it hath an intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall virtue, but in a power yet more remote &amp; further off, ſo we finde by experience, that one and the ſame ſoule is firſt in act inregard of the inferior powers, and afterwards in regard of the ſuperior that firſt he is an animall man before a ſpirituall man.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe we know by proofe that there is a certaine numerall virtue in the Bowells of the earth which may alſo be called a
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:120060:95"/>ſpirit, and that it is firſt in power or poſſibility to be made a mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra of ſtone, and another to bee made a minera of Salt, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Mettall, and that there are divers ſuch ſpirits according to the diverſity of Sones, Salts, and Mettalls, but yet that there is one ſpirit of the Minera of Gold, which by the influence of the Sun, or of the Heaven, is continually more and more pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, and at length fixed into ſuch Gold as is not by any Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be corrupted or diſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that in it there ſhines exceeding much of the incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible light of heaven, for it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry like the corporall light of the Sun.</p>
               <p>And the like wee finde alſo of the vegitable and ſenſitive ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for the ſenſitive ſpirit in a man doth much conforme it ſelfe unto the moving and influentiall
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:120060:95"/>virtue of Heaven, and doth ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively take increaſe under the influence of Heaven; untill it be put in perfect act: And it is brought out of the power or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of the body, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the perfection of it ceaſeth as ſoone as the perfection of the body faileth.</p>
               <p>Then is there an intellectuall ſpirit which in the act of its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection depends not of the body but is united unto it by meanes of the ſenſitive virtue, This ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit becauſe it dependeth not of the body, is not ſubject to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the heaven, by bodies, neither depends it of the ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſpirit, and ſo not of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving power of Heaven; but as the movers of the heavenly.</p>
               <p>Orbs are ſubject to the firſt mover, ſo likewiſe this mover, which is the underſtanding, but becauſe it is united to the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:120060:96"/>bodie by the meane of the ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power, therefore it is not perfected without the ſences, for all that comes unto it from the ſenſible world comes unto it by meanes of the ſences.</p>
               <p>And therefore there can bee nothing in the underſtanding which hath not firſt bin in the ſence; And by how much the ſenſe is purer and perfecter, and the imagination clearer, and the diſcourſe bitter, by ſo much the underſtanding in its intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all operations is leſſe hindered, and more perſpicatious.</p>
               <p>Now the underſtanding is fed by the word of life, under whoſe ifluence it is placed as the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Orbs but differently, as alſo the ſpirits that are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the influences of Heaven are differently perfected: And it is not perfected but acceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally by the ſenſible ſpirit as the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:120060:96"/>Image doth not perfect, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it excite to enquire the truth of the ſamplar or patterne, as the Image of the Crucified doth not inflow devotion; but ſtirsup the memory that devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be inflowed, and becauſe the intellectuall ſpirit is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated by the influence of Heaven, but is wholy free, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore except it do by faith ſubject it ſelfe unto the influence of the word of God, it is not perfected as a Schollar that is free, and in his owne power, unleſſe he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject himſelfe unto the word of his Maſter, by beleeveing hee is not perfected for hee muſt truſt and heare his Maſter.</p>
               <p>And the underſtanding is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by the word of God, and growes, and is made every day more capable and apt, and more like to the word, And this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which thus comes from
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:120060:97"/>the word from whence it had its being, is not a corruptible perfection, but a perfection dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme or formed by God, as the perfection of Gold is not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, but of the forme of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And every underſtanding muſt by faith ſubject it ſelfe to the word of God, and moſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively harken to that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall teaching of the higheſt Mr. and by hearing what the Lord ſaith in it, It ſhall bee perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Wherefore thou O Jeſus the only Maſter hath preached, that faith is neceſſary for every one that comes to the fountaine of life, and haſt ſhewne that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the degree of faith, the influence of the divine power is preſent. O Saviour Chriſt, two things only haſt thou taught, Faith and Love: By faith the underſtanding comes to the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:120060:97"/>word, and by love it is united to it, By how much more it comes unto it, by ſo much more it is increaſed in power, and by how much more it loveth, by ſo much more it is fixed to the light thereof, and the word of God is within it, [the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding] and it needs not ſeeke for it without it ſelfe, for hee ſhall finde it within, and by faith hee ſhall approach unto it.</p>
               <p>And that hee may come nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer hee ſhall obtaine by prayers, for the word will increaſe faith, by the Communication of its light.</p>
               <p>I give thee thanks O Jeſus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by thy light I am come thus farre, for in thy light, I ſee the light of my life, how thou the word infloweſt, life to all that beleeve and perfecteſt all that love thee. What other Doctrine was ever ſo ſhort and
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:120060:98"/>effectuall as thine O good Jeſus, thou perſwadeſt nothing but to beleeve, and thou commandeſt nothing but to love, What is more eaſie then to beleeve God, what more ſweet than to love him? How ſweet is thy Yok; and how light is thy burthen O ray Mr. thou promiſeſt to them that keepe this Doctrine, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can be deſired, for thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt nothing that is hard to him that beleeves, nothing deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him that loves. Such are the promiſes thou makeſt to thy Diſciples and they are moſt true becauſe thou art truth which canſt promiſe nothing but true things, nay thou promiſeſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but thy ſelfe, who art the perfection of every thing that may be perfected. To thee bee praiſe, to thee be Glory, to thee be thankſgiving through all ages <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:120060:98"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Ieſus is the conſumation.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. 25.</head>
               <p>YEt what may that be O Lord that thou ſendeſt into the ſpirit of that man whom thou perfecteſt? Is it not thy good ſpirit which is wholly in Act, the vertue and power of all vertues, and the perfection of all perfect things, becauſe it is hee that worketh all things. For as the power of the Sunne deſcending into the vegitable ſpirit, moves it that it may be perfected, and ſo by the meanes of a good Tree, there is made good fruit, but a moſt acceptable and naturall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of a heavenly heate. So thy ſpirit O God comes into the intellectual ſpirit of Good men, and by the heat of divine love, concocts the virtuall power that
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:120060:99"/>it may be perfected, and made moſt acceptable fruit unto it.</p>
               <p>We finde by experience that thy ſimple ſpirit infinite in vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is many wayes received: for it is otherwiſe received in one where it maks a prophetick ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, &amp; otherwiſe in another where it makes a cunning and skilfull interpretor, and otherwiſe in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other where it teacheth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and otherwiſe in other men, For there are divers gifts thereof, and they are the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the intellectuall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit as the ſame heat of the ſume in divers Trees perfecteth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers fruits.</p>
               <p>I ſee O Lord that thy ſpirit is not wanting to any ſpirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the ſpirit of ſpirits, and the motion of motions and it filleth all the world, but it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth all things which have not
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:120060:99"/>the intellectual ſpirit by that in tellectuall nature, which moves the Heaven, and by the motion thereof all things that are under it, only the diſpoſition and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation in the intellectuall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it hath reſerved unto it ſelfe a Love: For it hath eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to it ſelfe this nature, in which it hath choſen to reſt as in a Mantion houſe, and in the Haven of truth, for no where els can this truth be received in it ſelfe, but in the intellectuall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Thou O Lord which workeſt all things for thy ſelfe haſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this whole world for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall nature. As a Painter which tempreth divers Colours, that at length hee may paint himſelfe, to the end hee may have his owne Image that his Art may therein reſt and take delight, that ſo being himſelfe
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:120060:100"/>one and unmultipliable at the leaſt, hee may be multiplyed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the beſt manner poſſible in the neereſt ſimilitude. And Hee makes many figures becauſe the ſimilitude of his infinit virtue &amp; power cannot bee after a more perfect manner explicated, but in many things and all intellectuall ſpirits are to every ſpirit oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. For if they were not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, thou being an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite God couldſt not be known after the beſt manner: for every intellectuall ſpirit ſeeth ſome thing in the my God, which if it were not revealed unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers they ſhould not approach unto thee their God after the beſt manner poſſible. Therefore the ſpirit being full of love, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale their ſecrets one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and by this meanes the knowledge of the beloved is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and the deſire unto it,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:120060:100"/>and the ſweerneſſe of joy is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed.</p>
               <p>Neither yet O Lord God haſt thou made the accompliſhment; of thy work without Jeſus thy Sonne whom thou anoyntedſt above his fellowes, who is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt, In whoſe underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding reſts the perfection of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry creatable nature, for it is the laſt and perfecteſt unmultipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able likeneſſe of God, and there can bee no one ſuch ſupreame one: For all other intellctuall ſpirits are by the mediation of that ſpirit ſimilitudes, and by how much more perfect, ſo much more like unto it, And they all reſt in that ſpirit, as in the laſt of perfection of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, of which Image they have attained ſome ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and degree of perfection.</p>
               <p>I have therefore by thy guift O God all this viſible world, and
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:120060:101"/>all the ſcripture, and all admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring ſpirits to helpe me profit in the knowledge of thee, all things excite mee to be turned to thee.</p>
               <p>All Scriptures labour for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to ſhew thee, all intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall ſpirits have no other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe but to ſeeke thee and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale what they have found of thee. Above all things thou haſt given me Jeſus for a Maſter the way of life, and the truth, that ſo there might bee nothing at all wanting unto mee.</p>
               <p>Thou comforteſt me by thy holy ſpirit, by it thou inſpireſt the choiſe of life, holy deſires: Thou aſureſt mee by a foretaſte of the ſweetneſſe of that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life to love thee the infinite good.</p>
               <p>Thou raviſheſt mee that I am above my ſelfe, and do before hand ſee that place of glory to
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:120060:101"/>which thou inviteſt mee, Thou ſheweſt mee many delicate and ſavorie diſhes that draw mee by their moſt excellent odour, thou ſuffereſt mee to ſee the treaſure of riches, life, joy, beauty, Thou diſcovereſt the fountaine from whence flowes every deſireable thing as wel in nature as in art, Thou keepeſt nothing ſecret, thou hideſt not the vaine of love, nor peace, nor reſt.</p>
               <p>Thou offerſt all things to me moſt miſerable man whom thou haſt created of nothing.</p>
               <p>Why do I therefore ſtay? why doe I not runne after my Chriſt in the odour of this oyntments? Why do I not enter into the joy of my Maſter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me if ignorance of thee O Lord and the vaine delights of this ſencible world have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden me it ſhall now hold me
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:120060:102"/>no longer, for I will O Lord (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou giveſt mee power to will) leave the things of this world, becauſe the world will leave mee, I make haſt to the end I have almoſt finiſhed my courſe I will prevent the world in bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it farewell, becauſe I labour towards the Crowne, draw mee O Lord (for no man can come to thee except he bee drawne by thee) that being drawne by thee, I may be freed from this world and joyne to thee the abſolute God in the eternity of a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:120060:102"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
